<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The night-walker, or, The little thief a comedy as it was presented by Her Majesties servants at the private house in Drury-Lane / written by John Fletcher, Gent.</title>
            <author>Fletcher, John, 1579-1625.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 171 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39806</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1347</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29426</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11132542</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11132542</idno>
            <idno type="VID">46367</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39806)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 46367)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1423:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The night-walker, or, The little thief a comedy as it was presented by Her Majesties servants at the private house in Drury-Lane / written by John Fletcher, Gent.</title>
                  <author>Fletcher, John, 1579-1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>70 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Andrew Crook,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:46367:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46367:1"/>
            <p>THE NIGHT-VVALKER, OR THE <hi>LITTLE THIEF.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A COMEDY, As it was preſented by her Majeſties Servants, at the Private Houſe in DRURY-LANE.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>John Fletcher,</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Andrew Crook,</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:46367:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46367:2"/>
            <head>THE <hi>NIGHT-WALKER:</hi> OR, THE <hi>LITTLE THIEF.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>Actus primus, Scena prima.</head>
               <stage>Enter Tom Lurcher and Iack Wildbrain.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lurc.</speaker>
                  <l>IAcke.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <l>What winde brought thee hither?</l>
                  <l>In what hollow tree, or rotten wall</l>
                  <l>Haſt thou been like a Swallow all this Winter,</l>
                  <l>Where haſt thou been man?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Following the Plow.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <l>What plow?</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt no Land,</l>
                  <l>Stealing is thy own purchaſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>The beſt inheritance.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <l>Not in my opinion,</l>
                  <l>Thou hadſt five hundred pound a year.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis gone,</l>
                  <l>Prethee no more on't, have I not told thee,</l>
                  <l>And oftentimes, nature made all men equal,</l>
                  <l>Her diſtribution to each child alike;</l>
                  <l>Till labour came and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſt a new Will in,</l>
                  <l>Which I allow not: till men won a priviledge</l>
                  <l>By that they call endeavour, which indeed</l>
                  <l>Is nothing but a lawful Coſenage,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:3"/>
                  <l>An allowed way to cheat, why ſhould my neighbour</l>
                  <l>That hath no more ſoul than his Horſe-keeper,</l>
                  <l>Nor bounteous faculties above a Broom-man,</l>
                  <l>Have fourty thouſand pound, and I four groats;</l>
                  <l>Why ſhould he keep it?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Will.</speaker>
                  <l>Thy old opinion ſtill.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Why ſhould that Scrivener</l>
                  <l>That ne're writ reaſon in his life, nor any thing</l>
                  <l>That time ere gloried in, that never knew</l>
                  <l>How to keep any curteſie conceal'd,</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Noverint univerſi</hi> muſt proclaim it,</l>
                  <l>Purchaſe perpetually, and I a raſcal:</l>
                  <l>Conſider this, why ſhould that mouldy Cobler</l>
                  <l>Marry his daughter to a wealthy Merchant,</l>
                  <l>And give five thouſand pound, is this good juſtice?</l>
                  <l>Becauſe he has a tougher conſtitution;</l>
                  <l>Can feed upon old ſongs, and ſave his money,</l>
                  <l>Therefore muſt I go beg?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>What's this to thee?</l>
                  <l>Thou canſt not mend, if thou beeſt determin'd</l>
                  <l>To rob all like a tyrant, yet take heed</l>
                  <l>A keener juſtice do not overtake thee,</l>
                  <l>And catch you in a Nooze.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>I am no Wood-cock,</l>
                  <l>He that ſhall ſit down frighted with that foolery</l>
                  <l>Is not worth pity, let me alone to ſhuffle,</l>
                  <l>Thou art for wenching.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>For beauty I, a ſafe courſe,</l>
                  <l>No halter hangs in the way, I defie it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>But a worſe fate, a wilful poverty,</l>
                  <l>For where thou gainſt by one that indeed loves thee,</l>
                  <l>A thouſand will draw from thee, 'tis thy deſtiny;</l>
                  <l>One is a kind of weeping croſs <hi>Iack,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A gentle purgatory, do not fling at all,</l>
                  <l>You'le pay the Box ſo often, till you periſh.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>Take you no care for that ſir, 'tis my pleaſure,</l>
                  <l>I will imploy my wits a great deal faſter</l>
                  <l>Then you ſhall do your ſingers, and my Loves,</l>
                  <l>If I miſtake not, ſhall prove riper harveſt</l>
                  <l>And handſomer, and come within leſs danger.</l>
                  <l>Where's thy young ſiſter?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>I Know not where ſhe is, ſhe is not worth caring for,</l>
                  <l>She has no wit.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:3"/>
                  <l>Oh you'd be nibling with her,</l>
                  <l>She's far enough I hope, I know not where,</l>
                  <l>She's not worth caring for, a fullen thing,</l>
                  <l>She wo'd not take my counſel <hi>Iack,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And ſo I parted from her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>Leave her to her wants?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>I gave her a little money what I could ſpare,</l>
                  <l>She had a mind to th' Countrey, she is turn'd</l>
                  <l>By this ſome Farriers dairy maid, I may meet her</l>
                  <l>Riding from market one day 'twixt her Dorſers,</l>
                  <l>If I do, by this hand I wo' not ſpare</l>
                  <l>Her butter pence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou wilt not rob thy ſiſter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>She ſhall account me for her Egges and Cheeſes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>A pretty Girle, did not old <hi>Algript</hi> love her?</l>
                  <l>A very pretty Girle ſhe was.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Some ſuch thing,</l>
                  <l>But he was too wiſe to faſten; let her paſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>Then where's thy Miſtreſs?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Where you ſha'not find her,</l>
                  <l>Nor know what ſtuffe ſhe is made on, no indeed ſir,</l>
                  <l>I choſe her not for your uſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>Sure ſhe is handſome.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes indeed is ſhe, ſhe is very handſome, but that's all one.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>You'le come toth' marriage.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Is it to day.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>Now, now, they are come from Church now.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Any great preparation,</l>
                  <l>Does Juſtice <hi>Algripe</hi> ſhew his power.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>Very glorious, and glorious people there.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>I may meet with him yet e're I dye as cunning as he is.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>You may do good <hi>Tom</hi> at the marriage,</l>
                  <l>We have plate and dainty things.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Do you no harm ſir;</l>
                  <l>For yet me thinks the marriage ſhould be mar'd</l>
                  <l>If thou maiſt have thy will, farewel, ſay nothing. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     <stage>Enter Gentlemen.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>You are welcome noble friends.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1.</speaker>
                  <l>I thank you ſir,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>Nephew to the old Lady, his name is <hi>Wildbrain,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And wild his beſt condition.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2.</speaker>
                  <l>I have heard of him,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>I pray ye tell me ſir, is young <hi>Maria</hi> merry</l>
                  <l>After her marriage rites? does ſhe look lively?</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:4"/>
                  <l>How does ſhe like her man?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>Very ſcurvely,</l>
                  <l>And as untowardly she prepares her ſelf,</l>
                  <l>But 'tis mine Aunts will, that this dull mettal</l>
                  <l>Muſt be mixt with her to allay her handſomeneſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1.</speaker>
                  <l>Had <hi>Heartlove</hi> no faſt friends?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>His means are little,</l>
                  <l>And where thoſe littles are, as little comforts</l>
                  <l>Ever keep company: I know ſhe loves him,</l>
                  <l>His memory beyond the hopes of—</l>
                  <l>Beyond the <hi>Indies</hi> in his mouldy Cabinets,</l>
                  <l>But 'tis her unhandſome fate. <stage>Enter Heartlove.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1.</speaker>
                  <l>I am ſorry for't,</l>
                  <l>Here comes poor <hi>Frank,</hi> nay we are friends, ſtart not Sir,</l>
                  <l>We ſee you'r willow and are ſorry for't,</l>
                  <l>And though it be a wedding we are half mourners.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Good Gentlemen remember not my fortunes,</l>
                  <l>They are not to be help'd by words.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>Look up man,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A</hi> proper ſenſible fellow and ſhrink for a Wench,</l>
                  <l>Are there no more? or is ſhe all the handſomeneſs?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Prethee leave fooling.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>Prethee leave thou whining,</l>
                  <l>Have maids forgot to love?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>You are injurious.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>Let 'em alone a while, thei'le follow thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1,</speaker>
                  <l>Come good <hi>Frank.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Forget now, ſince there is no remedy,</l>
                  <l>And ſhew a merry face, as wiſe men would do.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2.</speaker>
                  <l>Be a free gueſt, and think not of thoſe paſſages.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>Think how to nick him home, thou knoweſt ſhe dotes on thee;</l>
                  <l>Graff me a dainty medler on his crabſtocke;</l>
                  <l>Pay me the dreaming puppy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Well, make your mirth, the whilſt I bear my miſery:</l>
                  <l>Honeſt minds would have better thoughts.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>I am her kinſman,</l>
                  <l>And love her well, am tender of her youth,</l>
                  <l>Yet honeſt <hi>Frank,</hi> before I would have that ſtinkard,</l>
                  <l>That walking rotten tombe, enjoy her maidenhead.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Prethee leave mocking.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>Prethee <hi>Frank</hi> believe me,</l>
                  <l>Go to conſider, harke, they kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ck to dinner. <stage>Kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ck within.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Come wo't thou go?</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:4"/>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2.</speaker>
                  <l>I preethee <hi>Frank</hi> go with us,</l>
                  <l>And laugh and dance as we do.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>You are light Gentlemen,</l>
                  <l>Nothing to weigh your hearts, pray give me leave,</l>
                  <l>Ile come and ſee, and take my leave.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>Wee'le look for you,</l>
                  <l>Do not deſpair, I have a trick yet. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes,</l>
                  <l>When I am miſchievous I will believe your projects:</l>
                  <l>She is gone, for ever gone, I cannot help it,</l>
                  <l>My hopes and all my happineſs gone with her.</l>
                  <l>Gone like a pleaſing dream: what mirth and jollity</l>
                  <l>Raignes round about this houſe? how every office</l>
                  <l>Sweats with new joyes, can ſhe be merry too?</l>
                  <l>Is all this pleaſure ſet by her appointment?</l>
                  <l>Sure ſhe hath a falſe heart then; ſtill they grow lowder,</l>
                  <l>The old mans God, his gold, has won upon her</l>
                  <l>(Light hearted Cordial gold) and all my ſervices</l>
                  <l>That offered naked truth, are clean forgotten:</l>
                  <l>Yet if ſhe were compel'd, but it cannot be,</l>
                  <l>If I could but imagine her will mine, <stage>Enter Lady and Wildbrain.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Although he had her body.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>He ſhall come in.</l>
                  <l>Walk without doors o' this day, though an enemy,</l>
                  <l>It muſt not be.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>You muſt compel him Madam,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>No ſhe ſhall fetch him in, Nephew it ſhall be ſo.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>It will be fitteſt. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Can fair <hi>Maria</hi> look agen upon me?</l>
                  <l>Can there be ſo much impudence in ſweetneſs?
<stage>Enter Maria.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or has ſhe got a ſtrong heart to defie me?</l>
                  <l>She comes her ſelf: how rich ſhe is in Jewels!</l>
                  <l>Me thinks they ſhow like frozen Iſicles,</l>
                  <l>Cold winter had hung on her, how the Roſes</l>
                  <l>That kept continual ſpring within her cheeks</l>
                  <l>Are witheered with old mans dull imbraces?</l>
                  <l>She would ſpeak to me. I can ſigh too Lady</l>
                  <l>But from a ſounder heart: yes, and can weep too</l>
                  <l>But 'tis for you, that ever I believ'd you,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:5"/>
                  <l>Tears of more pious value than your marriage;</l>
                  <l>You would encaſe your ſelf, and I muſt credit you,</l>
                  <l>So much my old obedience compels from me;</l>
                  <l>Go, and forget me, and my poverty,</l>
                  <l>I need not bid you, you are too perfect that way:</l>
                  <l>But ſtill remember that I lov'd <hi>Maria,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Lov'd with a loyal love, nay turn not from me,</l>
                  <l>I will not ask a treare more, you are bountiful,</l>
                  <l>Go and rejoyce, and I will wait upon you</l>
                  <l>That little of my life left.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>Good ſir hear me,</l>
                  <l>What has been done, was the act of my obedience</l>
                  <l>And not my will: forc'd from me by my parents,</l>
                  <l>Now 'tis done, do as I do, bear it handſomly</l>
                  <l>And if there can be more ſociety</l>
                  <l>Without diſhonour to my tye of marriage</l>
                  <l>Or place for noble love, I ſhall love you ſtill,</l>
                  <l>You had the firſt, the laſt, had my will proſper'd;</l>
                  <l>You talk of little time of life: dear <hi>Franke,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Certain I am not married for eternity,</l>
                  <l>The joy my marriage brings tells me I am mortal.</l>
                  <l>And ſhorter liv'd then you, elſe I were miſerable;</l>
                  <l>Nor can the gold and eaſe his age hath brought me</l>
                  <l>Adde what I coveted, content, go with me,</l>
                  <l>They ſeek a day of joy, prethce let's ſhow it,</l>
                  <l>Though it be forc'd, and by this kiſs believe me</l>
                  <l>However, I muſt live at his command now,</l>
                  <l>Ile dye at yours.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>I have enough, Ile honour ye. <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                     <stage>Enter Lurcher.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Here are my trinkets, and this luſty marriage</l>
                  <l>I mean to viſit, I have ſhift of all ſorts,</l>
                  <l>And here are a thouſand wheeles to ſet'em working,</l>
                  <l>I am very merry, for I know this wedding</l>
                  <l>Will yield me luſty pillage, if mad <hi>VVildgooſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That deboſh'd rogue keep but his antient revells,</l>
                  <l>And breed a hubbub in the houſe I am happy.
<stage>Enter Boy.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Now what are you?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>A poor diſtreſſed Boy Sir,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:5"/>
                  <l>Friendleſs and comfortleſs, that would entreat</l>
                  <l>Some charity and kindneſs from your worſhip,</l>
                  <l>I would fain ſerve Sir, and as fain indeavour</l>
                  <l>With dutious labour to deſerve the love</l>
                  <l>Of that good Gentleman ſhall entertain me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>A pretty boy, but of too milde a breeding,</l>
                  <l>Too tender and too baſhfull a behaviour,</l>
                  <l>What canſt thou do?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy</speaker>
                  <l>I can learn any thing,</l>
                  <l>That's good and honeſt, and ſhall pleaſe Maſter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>He bluſhes as he ſpeaks, and that I like not,</l>
                  <l>I love a bold and ſecure confidence,</l>
                  <l>An impudence that one may truſt, this boy now</l>
                  <l>Had I inſtructed him had been a Jewel,</l>
                  <l>A treaſure for my uſe, thou canſt not lye.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>I would not willingly.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Nor thou haſt not wit</l>
                  <l>To diſſemble neatly.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Do you love ſuch boyes, Sir?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh mainly, mainly, I would have my boy impudent,</l>
                  <l>Out-face all truth, yet do it piouſly:</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Proteus,</hi> caſt himſelf into all forms,</l>
                  <l>As ſudden and as nimble as his thoughts,</l>
                  <l>Blanch at no danger, though it be the Gallowes,</l>
                  <l>Nor make no conſcience of a coſonage</l>
                  <l>Though it be ith' Church; your ſoft, demure, ſtill children—</l>
                  <l>Are good for nothing, but to get long graces—</l>
                  <l>And ſing ſongs to dull tunes; I would keep thee</l>
                  <l>And cheriſh thee, hadſt thou any active quality,</l>
                  <l>And be a tender Maſter to thy knavery,</l>
                  <l>But thou art not for my uſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Do you ſpeak this ſeriouſly?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes indeed do I.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Would you have your boy Sir</l>
                  <l>Read in theſe moral miſchiefs?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Now thou mov'ſt me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>And be a well train'd youth in all activities?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>By any means.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Or do you this to try me,</l>
                  <l>Fearing a proneneſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſpeake this to make thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Then take me Sir, and cheriſh me, and love me,</l>
                  <l>You have me what you would: believe me Sir</l>
                  <l>I can do any thing for your advantage,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:6"/>
                  <l>I gueſs at what you mean; I can can lie naturally,</l>
                  <l>As eaſily, as I can ſleep Sir, and ſecurely:</l>
                  <l>As naturally I can ſteal too.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>That I am glad on,</l>
                  <l>Right heartily glad on, hold thee there, thou art excellent.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Steal any thing from any body living.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Not from thy Maſter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
                  <l>That's mine own body:</l>
                  <l>And muſt not be.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>The Boy mends mightily.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
                  <l>A rich man, that like ſnow, heaps up his moneys,</l>
                  <l>I have a kind of pious zeal to meet ſtill;</l>
                  <l>A fool that not deſerves 'em, I take pitty on,</l>
                  <l>For fear he ſhould run mad, and ſo I eaſe him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Excellent boy, and able to inſtruct me,</l>
                  <l>Of my own nature juſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſcorn all hazard,</l>
                  <l>And on the edge of danger I do beſt ſir,</l>
                  <l>I h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ve a thouſand faces to deceive,</l>
                  <l>And to thoſe twice ſo many tongues to flatter,</l>
                  <l>An impudence, no braſs was ever tougher,</l>
                  <l>And for my conſcience.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Peace, I have found a Jewel,</l>
                  <l>A Jewel all the Indies cannot match,</l>
                  <l>And thou ſha't feel—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>This title, and I ha'done ſir;</l>
                  <l>I never can confeſs, I ha' that ſpell on me;</l>
                  <l>And ſuch rare modeſties before a Magiſtrate,</l>
                  <l>Such Innocence to catch a Judge, ſuch ignorance.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile learn of thee, thou art mine own, come Boy,</l>
                  <l>Ile give thee action preſently.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Have at you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>What muſt I call thee?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Snap ſir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis moſt natural,</l>
                  <l>A name born to thee, ſure thou art a Fairie,</l>
                  <l>Shew but thy skill, and I ſhall make thee happie.
<stage>Enter Lady, Nurſe, Miſtreſs, Newlove, Tobie.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Where be theſe Knaves? who ſtrues up all the liveries.</l>
                  <l>Is the brides bed made?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tob.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes Madam and a bell</l>
                  <l>Hung under it artificially.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Out knave out,</l>
                  <l>Muſt we have larums now?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tob.</speaker>
                  <l>A little warning</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:6"/>
                  <l>That we may know when to begin our healths Madam,</l>
                  <l>The Juſtice is a kinde of old Jade Madam,</l>
                  <l>That will go mer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ieſt with a bell.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>All the houſe drunk.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tob.</speaker>
                  <l>This is a day of Jubile.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e the beſt hangings up, and the plate ſet out?</l>
                  <l>Who makes the Poſſet, Nurſe?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>The dairie mayd,</l>
                  <l>And ſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'le put that in, will make him caper:</l>
                  <l>Well Madam, well, you might ha'choſe another,</l>
                  <l>A handſomer for your years.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Peace, he is rich Nurſe,</l>
                  <l>He is rich, and that's beauty.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>I am ſure he is rotten,</l>
                  <l>Would he had been hang'd when he firſt ſaw her. <hi>Termagant!</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>What an angry quean is this, where,</l>
                  <l>Who looks to him?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tob.</speaker>
                  <l>He is very merry Madam,</l>
                  <l>M. <hi>Wildbrain,</hi> has him in hand, ith' bottom oth' Sellar</l>
                  <l>He ſighes and tipples.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas good Gentleman,</l>
                  <l>My heart's ſore for thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Sorrow muſt have his courſe, ſirra,</l>
                  <l>Give him ſome Sack to dry up his remembrance,</l>
                  <l>How does the Bridegroom, I am afraid of him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>He is a trim youth to be tender of, hemp take him.</l>
                  <l>Muſt my ſweet new blown Roſe find ſuch a winter</l>
                  <l>Before her ſpring be near.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Peace, peace, thou art fooliſh.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>And dances like a Town-top: and reels, and hobbles.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas, good Gentleman, give him not much wine,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tob.</speaker>
                  <l>He ſhall ha' none by my conſent.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Are the women comforting my daughter?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>New.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, yes, Madam,</l>
                  <l>And reading to her a pattern of true patience,</l>
                  <l>They read and pray for her too.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>They had need,</l>
                  <l>Ye had better marry her to her grave a great deal:</l>
                  <l>There will be peace and reſt, alas poor Gentlewoman,</l>
                  <l>Muſt ſhe become a Nurſe now in her tenderneſs?</l>
                  <l>Well Madam, well my heart bleeds.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb facs="tcp:46367:7"/>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou art a fool ſtill.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>Pray heaven I be.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>And an old fool to be vext thus.</l>
                  <l>Tis late ſhe muſt to bed, go knave be merry,</l>
                  <l>Drinke for a boy, away to all your charges. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     <stage>Enter Wildbrain, and Franke Heartlove.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>Do as thou wo't, but if thou doſt refuſe it</l>
                  <l>Thou art the ſtupid'ſt aſſe, there's no long arguing,</l>
                  <l>Time is too precious <hi>Franke.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>I am hot with wine,</l>
                  <l>And apt now to believe, but if thou doſt this.</l>
                  <l>Out of a villany, to make me wrong her,</l>
                  <l>As thou art prone enough.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>Does ſhe not love thee?</l>
                  <l>Did ſhe not cry down-right e'en now to part with thee?</l>
                  <l>Had she not ſwounded if I had not caught her?</l>
                  <l>Canſt thou have more?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>I muſt confeſs all this.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>Do not ſtand prating, and miſdoubting, caſting,</l>
                  <l>If ſhe go from thee now, ſhe's loſt for ever;</l>
                  <l>Now now ſhe's going, ſhe that loves thee going,</l>
                  <l>She whom thou lov'ſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Pray let me think a little:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>There is no leiſure; think when thou haſt imbrace'd her.</l>
                  <l>Can ſhe imagine thou didſt ever honour her?</l>
                  <l>Ever believe thy oathes, that tamely ſuffer'ſt</l>
                  <l>An old dry ham of horſe-fleſh to enjoy her?</l>
                  <l>Enjoy her Maiden head; take but that from her</l>
                  <l>That we may tell poſterity a man had it,</l>
                  <l>A handſome man, a gentleman, a young man,</l>
                  <l>To ſave the honour of our houſe, the credit,</l>
                  <l>Tis no great matter I deſire.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>I hear you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>Free us both from the fear of breeding fools</l>
                  <l>And ophs, got by this ſhadow: we talke too long.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>She is going to bed, among the women,</l>
                  <l>What opportunity can I have to meet her?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>Let me alone, haſt thou a will? ſpeak ſoundly,</l>
                  <l>Speak diſcreetly, ſpeak home and handſomely,</l>
                  <l>Iſt not pitty, nay miſery, nay inſamy to leave</l>
                  <l>So rare a pie to be cut up by a raskall.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>I will go preſently, now, now, I ſtay thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb facs="tcp:46367:7"/>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>Such a dainty Doe, to be taken</l>
                  <l>By one that knows not necke-beefe from a Pheſant,</l>
                  <l>Nor cannot relliſh Braggat from Ambroſia.</l>
                  <l>Is it not conſcience?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, yes, now I feel it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>A meritorious thing.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Good Father Wildgooſe,</l>
                  <l>I do confeſs it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>Come then follow me.</l>
                  <l>And pluck a mans heart up, Ile locke thee privately,</l>
                  <l>Where ſhe alone ſhall preſently paſs by,</l>
                  <l>None near to interupt thee but be ſure;</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhall be ſure enough, lead on, and crown me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>No wringings in your mind now as you love me. <stage>Ex.</stage>
                     <stage>Enter Lady, Maria, Iuſtice, Gent. Nurſe, Newlove.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis time you were a bed.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>I prethee ſweet-heart</l>
                  <l>Conſider my neceſſity, why art ſad?</l>
                  <l>I muſt tell you a tale in your ear anon.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>Of <hi>Tom Thumb.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I believe that will prove your ſtiffeſt ſtory.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>New.</speaker>
                  <l>I pitty the young wench.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1.</speaker>
                  <l>And ſo do I too.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2.</speaker>
                  <l>Come, old ſtickes take fire.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1.</speaker>
                  <l>But the Plague is, he'l burn out inſtantly;</l>
                  <l>Give him another cup.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2.</speaker>
                  <l>Thoſe are but flaſhes,</l>
                  <l>A tun of ſack wonot ſet him high enough.</l>
                  <l>Will ye to bed?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>I muſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1.</speaker>
                  <l>Come, have a good heart,</l>
                  <l>And win him like a bowle to lye cloſe to you,</l>
                  <l>Make your beſt uſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ju.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay prethee Duck go inſtantly,</l>
                  <l>Ile daunce a Jig or two to warme my body.
<stage>Enter Wildbrain.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis almoſt midnight.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Prethee to bed <hi>Maria.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>Go you afore, and let the Ladies follow,</l>
                  <l>And leave her to her thoughts a while, there muſt be</l>
                  <l>A time of taking leave of the ſame fooleries</l>
                  <l>Bewailing others maiden-heads.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Come then,</l>
                  <l>We'l wait in the nex room.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb facs="tcp:46367:8"/>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>Do not tarry.</l>
                  <l>For if thou doſt, by my troth I ſhall fall aſleep <hi>Mall.</hi> 
                     <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Do, do, and dream of D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rells, get you to bed quickly,</l>
                  <l>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d let us ha'no more ſtir, come no, crying,</l>
                  <l>'Tis too late now, carry your ſelves diſcreetly.</l>
                  <l>The old thief loves thee dearly, thats the benefit.</l>
                  <l>For the reſt you muſt make your own play, Nay not that way,</l>
                  <l>Theil pull ye all to pieces, for your whim-whams,</l>
                  <l>Your garters and your gloves, go modeſtly,</l>
                  <l>And privately ſteal to bed, 'tis very late <hi>Mall,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For if you go by them ſuch a new larum.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <l>I know not which way to avoid'em.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>This way,</l>
                  <l>This through the Cloiſters: and ſo ſteal to bed,</l>
                  <l>When you are there once, all will ſeparate</l>
                  <l>And give ye reſt, I came out of my pity</l>
                  <l>To ſhew you this.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <l>I thank you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Here's the keyes,</l>
                  <l>Go preſently and lock the doors faſt after ye,</l>
                  <l>That none ſhall follow.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <l>Good night.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Good night ſweet Coſen,</l>
                  <l>A good, and ſweet night, or Ile cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe thee <hi>Frank.</hi> 
                     <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     <stage>Enter Frank Hartlove.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
                  <l>She ſtayes long, ſure young <hi>Wildgooſe</hi> has abus'd me,</l>
                  <l>He has made ſport wi'me, I may yet get out again,</l>
                  <l>And I may ſee his face once more, I ha foul intentions,</l>
                  <l>But they are drawn on by a fouler dealing.
<stage>Enter Maria.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Hark, hark, it was the door,</l>
                  <l>Something comes this way, wondrous ſtill, and ſtealing</l>
                  <l>May be ſome walking ſpirit to affright me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh heaven my fortune.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis her voice, ſtay.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <l>Save me,</l>
                  <l>Bleſs me you better powers.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>I am no Devil.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <l>Y'are little better to diſturb me now.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>My name is <hi>Hartlove.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <l>Fye, fye, worthy friend.</l>
                  <l>Fye noble ſir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>I muſt talk farther with ye,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:8"/>
                  <l>You know my fair affection.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <l>So preſerve it,</l>
                  <l>You know I am married now, for ſhame be civiller,</l>
                  <l>Not all the earth ſhall make me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Pray walk this way,</l>
                  <l>And if you ever lov'd me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <l>Take heed <hi>Frank</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>How you divert that love to hate, go home prethee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Shall he enjoy that ſweet?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, pray unhand me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>He that never felt what love was.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <l>Then I charge you ſtand further off.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>I am tame, but let me walk wi'ye,</l>
                  <l>Talk but a minute.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r.</speaker>
                  <l>So your talk be honeſt,</l>
                  <l>And my untainted honour ſuffer not;</l>
                  <l>Ile walk a turn or two.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Give me your hand then. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     <stage>Enter, Wildbrain, Iustice, Lady, Nurſe, Gent. Women, Newlove.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iuſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Shee's not in her Chamber.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>She is not here.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>And Ile tell you what I dream'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>Give me a Torch.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1. G.</speaker>
                  <l>Be not too haſty fir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay let him go.</l>
                  <l>For if my dream be true, he muſt be ſpeedy,</l>
                  <l>He will be trickt, and blaz'd elſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>As I am a woman</l>
                  <l>I cannot blame her if ſhe take her liberty,</l>
                  <l>Would ſhe would make thee cuckold, thou old bully,</l>
                  <l>A notorious cuckold for tormenting her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile hang her then.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile bleſs her then, ſhe does juſtice,</l>
                  <l>Is this old ſtinking doggs fleſh for her dyet?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>Prethee honeſt Nurſe do not fret too much,</l>
                  <l>For fear I dream youle hang your ſelf too.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iuſt.</speaker>
                  <l>The Cloiſter?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>Such was my fancy, I do not ſay 'tis true,</l>
                  <l>Nor do I bid you be too confident.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>Where are the keyes, the keyes I ſay.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>I dream'd ſhe had'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m to lock her ſelf in.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>What a Devil do you mean?</l>
                  <stage>
                     <pb facs="tcp:46367:9"/>Enter Servant.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>No harme, good Nurſe be patient.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>They are not in the window, where they uſe to be.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>What fooliſh dreams are theſe?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>I am mad.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>I hope ſo,</l>
                  <l>If you be not mad, Ile do my beſt to make yee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1.</speaker>
                  <l>This is ſome tricke.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſmell the Wildgooſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>Come gentlemen, come quickely I beſeech you,</l>
                  <l>Quicke as you can, this may be your caſe Gentlemen.</l>
                  <l>And bring ſome lights, ſome lights. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>VVil.</speaker>
                  <l>Move faſter, faſter, you I come too late elſe.</l>
                  <l>Ile ſtay behind and pray for ye, I had rather she were dishoneſt,</l>
                  <l>Than thou shouldſt have her.
<stage>Enter Maria and Francke.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>Y're moſt unmanly. yet I have ſome breath left;</l>
                  <l>And this ſteel to defend me, come near me,</l>
                  <l>For if you offer but another violence,</l>
                  <l>As I have life Ile kill you, if I miſs that,</l>
                  <l>Vpon my own heart will I execute,</l>
                  <l>And let that fair beleefe out, I had of you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Moſt vertuous Maid, I have done, forgive my follies:</l>
                  <l>Pardon, O pardon, I now ſee my wickedneſs,</l>
                  <l>And what a monſtrous shape it puts upon me,</l>
                  <l>On your fair hand I ſeal. <stage>Enter Iu.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>Down with the door.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <l>We are betraid, oh <hi>Francke, Franke,</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile dye for ye</l>
                  <l>Rather than you shall ſuffer, Ile—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>Now Enter. <stage>Enter All.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Enter ſweet Gentlemen, mine eyes, mine eyes,</l>
                  <l>Oh how my head akes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1.</speaker>
                  <l>Is it poſſible?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2.</speaker>
                  <l>Hold her, she ſinkes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <l>A plot upon my honour</l>
                  <l>To poyſon my fair name, a ſtudied villany.</l>
                  <l>Farewell, as I have hope of peace, I am honeſt,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>My brains, my brains, my monſtrous brains, they bud ſure.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nu.</speaker>
                  <l>She is gone, she is gone.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb facs="tcp:46367:9"/>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>A handſome riddance of her.</l>
                  <l>Would I could as eaſily loſe her memory.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>Is this the ſweet of Marriage, have I bred thee</l>
                  <l>For this reward?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1.</speaker>
                  <l>Hold, hold, he's deſperate too.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ju.</speaker>
                  <l>Be ſure ye hold him faſt, weele bind him over</l>
                  <l>To the next Seſſions, and if I can, Ile hang him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay then Ile live to be a terrour to thee,</l>
                  <l>Sweet Virgin Roſe farewell: heaven has thy beauty,</l>
                  <l>That's onely fit for heaven. Ile live a little</l>
                  <l>To find the villain out that wrought this injury,</l>
                  <l>And then moſt bleſſed ſoul, Ile climbe up to thee.</l>
                  <l>Farewell, I feel my ſelf another creature. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh miſery of miſeries.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nu.</speaker>
                  <l>I told ye Madam.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Carry her in, you will pay back her portion.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ju.</speaker>
                  <l>No not a penny, pay me back my credit,</l>
                  <l>And Ile condition we'ye.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>A ſad wedding,</l>
                  <l>Her grave mnſt be her Bridal bed, oh <hi>Mall,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Would I had wed thee to thy own content,</l>
                  <l>Then I had had thee ſtill.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ju.</speaker>
                  <l>I am mad, farewell,</l>
                  <l>Another wanton wife will prove a hell. <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <head>Actus Secundus.</head>
               <l>
                  <stage>Enter Tom Lurch. and his Boy.</stage>
               </l>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>What haſt thou done?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>I have walked through all the lodgings.</l>
                  <l>A ſilence as if death dwelt there inhabits.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>What haſt thou ſeen?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Nought but a ſad confuſion</l>
                  <l>Every thing left in ſuch a looſe diſorder</l>
                  <l>That were there twenty theeves, they would be laden.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis very Well, I like thy care, but 'tis ſtrange</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:10"/>
                  <l>A wedding night ſhould be ſo ſolitary</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Certainly there is ſome cauſe, ſome death or ſickneſs</l>
                  <l>Is falne ſuddenly upon ſome friend,</l>
                  <l>Or ſome ſtrange news is come.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Are they all a bed?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>I think ſo, and ſound a ſleep, unleſs it be</l>
                  <l>Some women that keep watch in a low parlour,</l>
                  <l>And drink, and weep, I know not to what end.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Where's all the plate?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Why lockt up in that room.</l>
                  <l>I ſaw the old Lady, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re ſhe went to bed</l>
                  <l>Put up her plate, and ſome of the rich hangings</l>
                  <l>In a ſmal long cheſt, her chains and rings are there too,</l>
                  <l>It ſtands cloſe by the Table on a form.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>'Twas a good notice, didſt thou ſee the men.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſaw them ſad too, and all take their leaves,</l>
                  <l>But what they ſaid I was too far to her ſir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis daintily diſcover'd, we ſhall certainly</l>
                  <l>Have a moſt proſperous night, which way.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>A cloſe one,</l>
                  <l>A back door, that the women have left open,</l>
                  <l>To go in and out to fetch neceſſaries,</l>
                  <l>Cloſe on the Garden ſide.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>I love diligence,</l>
                  <l>Wert thou not fearful.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Fearful? Ile be hang'd firſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Say they had ſpied thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>I was then determin'd</l>
                  <l>To have cry'd down right too, and have kept 'em company,</l>
                  <l>As one that had an intereſt in their ſadneſs,</l>
                  <l>Or made an errand to I know not whom ſir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>My dainty Boy, let us diſcharge, that plate</l>
                  <l>Makes a perpetual motion in my fingers,</l>
                  <l>Till I have faſt hold of it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Pray be wiſe ſir, doe't handſomly, be not greedy,</l>
                  <l>Lets handle it with ſuch an excellence</l>
                  <l>As if we would bring theeving into honour:</l>
                  <l>We muſt diſguiſe, to fright theſe reverend watches.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb facs="tcp:46367:10"/>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Still my bleſt Boy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>And clear the Room of drunken jealouſies,</l>
                  <l>The cheſt is of ſome weight, and we may make</l>
                  <l>Such noiſe ith' the carriage we may be ſnap'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Come open, here's a Devils face.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>No, no, ſir, weele have no ſhape ſo terrible,</l>
                  <l>We will not do the Devil ſo much pleaſure,</l>
                  <l>To have him face our plot.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>A winding ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et then.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Thats too cold a ſhift,</l>
                  <l>I would not wear the reward of my wickedneſs,</l>
                  <l>I wonder you are an old thief, and no cunninger,</l>
                  <l>Where's the long Cloak?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Here, here.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Give me the Turbant</l>
                  <l>And the falſe beard, I hear ſome coming this way,</l>
                  <l>Stoop, ſtoop, and let me ſit upon your ſhoulders,</l>
                  <l>And now as I direct: ſtay let'em enter,</l>
                  <l>And when I touch move forward, make no noiſe.
<stage>Enter Nurſe and Tobie.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh 'its a ſad time, all the burnt wine is burnt Nick.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tob.</speaker>
                  <l>We may thank your dry chaps for't, the Canaries gone too</l>
                  <l>No ſubſtance for a ſorrowful mind to work upon,</l>
                  <l>I cannot mourn in beer, if ſhe ſhould walk now</l>
                  <l>As diſcontented ſpirits are wont to do.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>And meet us in the Cellar.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tob.</speaker>
                  <l>What fence have we with ſingle beer againſt her?</l>
                  <l>VVhat heart can we defie the Devil with?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>The March beer's open.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tob.</speaker>
                  <l>A fortification of March beer will do well,</l>
                  <l>I muſt co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>feſs 'tis a moſt mighty Armour,</l>
                  <l>For I preſume I cannot pray.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>VVhy <hi>Nicholas?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tob.</speaker>
                  <l>VVe Coachmen have ſuch tumbling faiths, no pray'rs</l>
                  <l>Can go an even pace.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>Hold up your candle.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tob.</speaker>
                  <l>Ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly Nurſe, I have cry'd ſo much</l>
                  <l>For my young M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtreſs, that is mortified,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:11"/>
                  <l>That if I have not more ſack to ſupport me;</l>
                  <l>I ſhall even ſleep, heiho, for another flagon;</l>
                  <l>Theſe Burials and Chriſtnings are the mournful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> matters,</l>
                  <l>And they ask more drink.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>Drink to a ſad heart's needful.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>Mine's ever ſad, for I am ever dry Nurſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>Me thinks the light burns blew, I prethee ſnuffe it,</l>
                  <l>There's a thief in't I think.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>There may be one near it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>Whats that that moves there, ith' name of—<hi>Nicholas?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That thing that walks.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>Would I had a ladder to behold it,</l>
                  <l>Mercy upon me, the Ghoſt of one oth' Guard ſure,</l>
                  <l>'Tis the devil by his clawes, he ſmalls of Brimſtone,</l>
                  <l>Sure he farts fire, what an Earth-quake I have in me;</l>
                  <l>Out with thy Prayer-book Nurſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>It ſelf ith' the frying-pan, and the Cat's eat it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tob.</speaker>
                  <l>I have no power to pray, it grows ſtill longer,</l>
                  <l>'Tis Steeple high now, and it ſails away Nurſe.</l>
                  <l>Lets call the Butler up, for he ſpeaks Latine,</l>
                  <l>And that will daunt the devil: I am blaſted,</l>
                  <l>My belly's grown to nothing.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nu.</speaker>
                  <l>Fye, fye, <hi>Tobi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 
                     <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
                  <l>So let them go, and whilſt they are aſtoniſh'd.</l>
                  <l>Let us preſently upon the reſt now ſuddenly.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Off, off, and up agen, when we are near the Parlour,</l>
                  <l>Art ſure thou knowſt the Cheſt?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Though it were ith' dark ſir,</l>
                  <l>I can go to't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>On then and be happy. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     <stage>Enter Tobie.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tob.</speaker>
                  <l>How my haunches quake, is the thing here ſtill?</l>
                  <l>Now can I out-do any Button-maker, at his own trade,</l>
                  <l>I have fifteen fits of an Ague, Nurſe, 'tis gone I hope,</l>
                  <l>The hard-hearted woman has left me alone. Nurſe—</l>
                  <l>And ſhe knows too I ha but a lean conſcience to keep me com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany. <stage>Noiſe within.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>The devil's among 'em in the Parlour ſure,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:11"/>
                  <l>The Ghoſt three ſtories high, he has the Nurſe ſure,</l>
                  <l>He is boyling of her bones now, hark how ſhe whiſtles:</l>
                  <l>There's Gentlewomen within too, how will they do?</l>
                  <l>Ile to the Cook, for he was drunk laſt night,</l>
                  <l>And now he is valiant, he is a kin to th' devil too,</l>
                  <l>And fears no fire,
<stage>Enter Lurcher and Boy.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>No light?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>None left ſir,</l>
                  <l>They are gone, and carried all the candles with 'em,</l>
                  <l>Their fright is infinite, let's make good uſe on't,</l>
                  <l>We muſt be quick ſir, quick, or the houſe will riſe elſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>VVas this the Cheſt?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, yes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>There was two of 'em.</l>
                  <l>Or I miſtake.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>I know the right, no ſtay ſir,</l>
                  <l>Nor no diſcourſe, but to our labour luſtily,</l>
                  <l>Put to your ſtrength and make as little noiſe,</l>
                  <l>Then preſently out at the back door.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Come Boy.</l>
                  <l>Come happy child and let me hug thy excellence. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     <stage>Enter Wildbrain.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>VVhat thouſand noiſes paſs through all the rooms?</l>
                  <l>VVhat cryes and hurries? ſure the devil's drunk.</l>
                  <l>And tumbles through the houſe, my villanies</l>
                  <l>That never made me apprehend before</l>
                  <l>Danger or fear, a little now moleſt me;</l>
                  <l>My Coſens death ſits heavy o'my conſcience,</l>
                  <l>VVould I had been half hang'd when I hammer'd it.</l>
                  <l>I aim'd at a living divorce, not a burial</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Frank</hi> might have had ſome hope: hark ſtill</l>
                  <l>In every room confuſion, they are all mad,</l>
                  <l>Moſt certain all ſtark mad within the houſe,</l>
                  <l>A puniſhment inflicted for my lewdneſs,</l>
                  <l>That I might have the more ſenſe of my miſchief,</l>
                  <l>And run the more mad too, my Aunt is hang'd ſure,</l>
                  <l>Sure hang'd her ſelf, or elſe the fiend has fetc'd her;</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:12"/>
                  <l>I heard a hundred cryes, the Devil, the Devil,</l>
                  <l>Then roaring and then tumbling, all the chambers</l>
                  <l>Are a meer Babel, or another Bedlam.</l>
                  <l>VVhat ſhould I think? I ſhake my ſelf too:</l>
                  <l>Can the Devil find no time, but when we are merry,</l>
                  <l>Here's ſomething comes. <stage>Enter Newlove.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>New.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh that I had ſome company,</l>
                  <l>I care not what they were, to eaſe my miſery,</l>
                  <l>To comfort me,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>VVhoſe that?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>New.</speaker>
                  <l>Again? noy then receive—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>Hold, hold I am no fury.</l>
                  <l>The Merchants wife,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>New.</speaker>
                  <l>Are ye a man? pray heaven you be.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>I am.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>New.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas I have met ſir</l>
                  <l>The ſtrangeſt things to night.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>VVhy do you ſtare.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>New.</speaker>
                  <l>Pray comfort me, and put your candle out,</l>
                  <l>For if I ſee the ſpirit again I dye for't.</l>
                  <l>And hold me faſt, for I ſhall ſhake to pieces elſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile warrant you, Ile hold ye,</l>
                  <l>Hold ye as tenderly; I have put the light out,</l>
                  <l>Retire into my Chamber, there Ile watch we'ye,</l>
                  <l>Ile keep you from all frights.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>New.</speaker>
                  <l>And will ye keep me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>Keep you as ſecure Lady.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>New.</speaker>
                  <l>You muſt not wrong me then, the devil will have us.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>No, no, Ile love you, then the devil will fear us.</l>
                  <l>For he fears all that love, pray come in quickly,</l>
                  <l>For this is the malicious houſe he walks in,</l>
                  <l>The hour he blaſts ſweet faces, lames the limbs in,</l>
                  <l>Depraves the ſenſes, now within this half hour</l>
                  <l>He will have power to turn all Citizens wives</l>
                  <l>Into ſtrange creatures, Owles, and long-taild Monkeys,</l>
                  <l>Jayes, Pies, and Parrots, quickly, I ſmell his brimſtone.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>New.</speaker>
                  <l>It comes agen I am gone ſhift for your ſelf ſir. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>VVil.</speaker>
                  <l>Sure this whole night is nothing but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lluſion,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:12"/>
                  <l>Here's nothing comes, all they are mad, damd devil</l>
                  <l>To drive her back agen, 't had been thy policy</l>
                  <l>To have let us alone, we might have done ſome fine thing</l>
                  <l>To have made thy hel-hood laugh, tis a dainty wench,</l>
                  <l>If I had her again, not all your fellow goblins</l>
                  <l>Nor all their clawes ſhould ſcratch her hence, Ile ſtay ſtill,</l>
                  <l>May be her fright will bring her back a gen,</l>
                  <l>Yet I will hope.
<stage>Enter Toby.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tob.</speaker>
                  <l>I can find no bed, no body, nor no chamber,</l>
                  <l>Sure they are all ith' Cellar, and I cannot find that neither,</l>
                  <l>I am led up and down like a tame aſs, my light's out</l>
                  <l>And I grope up and down like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lind-man buffe,</l>
                  <l>And break my face, and break <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>VVil.</speaker>
                  <l>It comes again ſure</l>
                  <l>I ſee the ſhadow, Ile have faſter hold now,</l>
                  <l>Sure ſhe is mad, I long to lye with a mad-woman,</l>
                  <l>She muſt needs have rare new tricks.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tob.</speaker>
                  <l>I hear one whiſper</l>
                  <l>If it be the devil now to allure me into his clutches,</l>
                  <l>For devils have a kind of tone like crickets,</l>
                  <l>I have a glimpſe of her guiſe, 'tis ſhe would ſteal me,</l>
                  <l>But Ile ſtand ſure.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tob.</speaker>
                  <l>I have but a dram of wit left,</l>
                  <l>And that's even ready to run, oh for my bed now.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>VVil.</speaker>
                  <l>She nam'd a bed, I like that, ſhe repents ſure,</l>
                  <l>Where is ſhe now?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tob.</speaker>
                  <l>Who's that?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>VVil.</speaker>
                  <l>Are you there, In, In, In preſently.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tob.</speaker>
                  <l>I feel his talents through me,</l>
                  <l>'Tis an old haggard devil, what will he do with me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>VVil.</speaker>
                  <l>Let me kiſs thee firſt, quick, quick.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tob.</speaker>
                  <l>A leacherous Devil.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>VVil.</speaker>
                  <l>What a hairy whore 'tis, ſure ſhe has a muffler.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tob.</speaker>
                  <l>If I ſhould have a young Satan by him, tor I dare not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny him,</l>
                  <l>In what caſe were I? who durſt deliver me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>VVil.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis but my fancy, ſhe is the ſame, in quickly, gently my</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:13"/>
                  <l>Sweet girle.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>Sweet devil be good to me. <stage>Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>nt.</stage>
                     <stage>Enter Lurch. and Boy.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>VVhere's my love, Boy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>She,s coming with a Candle</l>
                  <l>To ſee our happy prize.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>I am cruel weary.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>I cannot blame ye, plate is very heavy</l>
                  <l>To carry without light or help.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>The fear too</l>
                  <l>At every ſtumble to be diſcovered boy,</l>
                  <l>At every cough to raife a Conſtable,</l>
                  <l>VVell, wee'le be merry now.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>VVe have ſome reaſon;</l>
                  <l>Things compaſs'd without fear or eminent danger,</l>
                  <l>Are too luxurious ſir to live upon.</l>
                  <l>Money and wealth got thus are as full venture,</l>
                  <l>And carry in their nature as much merit</l>
                  <l>As his, that digs 'em out 'oth mine, they laſt too</l>
                  <l>Seaſon'd with doubts and dangers moſt delitiouſly,</l>
                  <l>Riches that fall upon us are too ripe,</l>
                  <l>And dull our appetites.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Moſt learned child.
<stage>Enter Miſtreſs.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                  <l>Y'are welcome, where have you left it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>in the next room, hard by.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                  <l>Is it plate all.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>All, all, and Jewels, I am monſtrous weary,</l>
                  <l>Prethee let's go to bed.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                  <l>Prethee let's ſee it firſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Tomorrow's a new day ſweet.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes to melt it,</l>
                  <l>But let's agree to night, how it ſhall be handled,</l>
                  <l>Ile have a new gown.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sur.</speaker>
                  <l>Shat have any thing.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                  <l>And ſuch a riding ſuite as Miſtreſs <hi>Newloves,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhat though I be no Gentlewoman born,</l>
                  <l>I hope I may atehieve it by my carriage.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou ſayſt right.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                  <l>You promis'd me a horſe too, and a lackquay.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou ſhat have horſes ſix, and a poſtilion.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb facs="tcp:46367:13"/>Mi.</speaker>
                  <l>That will be ſtately ſweet heart a poſtilion.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay wee'le be in faſhion he ſhall ride before us</l>
                  <l>In winter, with as much dirt would dampe a musket,</l>
                  <l>The inſide of our coach ſhall be of ſcarlet.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                  <l>That will be deer.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>There is a dye projecting</l>
                  <l>Will make it cheape wench, come thou ſhalt have any thing.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                  <l>Where is this cheſt, I long ſweete to behold</l>
                  <l>Our Jndies.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy</speaker>
                  <l>Miſtreſſe lets melt it firſt, and then tis ſit</l>
                  <l>You ſhould diſpoſe it, then tis ſafe from danger.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile be a loving Miſtreſſe to my boy too.</l>
                  <l>Now fetch it in and lets rejoyce upon't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Hold youre light Miſtreſſe, we may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e to enter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha whats here? call you this a cheſt?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy</speaker>
                  <l>We ha miſt ſir.</l>
                  <l>Our haſt and want of light made us miſtake.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                  <l>A very Coffin.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>How! a Coffin? Boy, Tis very like one.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>The devill ow'd us a ſhame, and now he has paid us.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                  <l>Is this your Treaſure?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy</speaker>
                  <l>Bury me alive in't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>It may be there is no roome.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, I will ſearch it:</l>
                  <l>Ile ſee what wealth's within,—a womans face,</l>
                  <l>And a faire womans.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>I cannot tell ſir,</l>
                  <l>Belike this was the ſadneſſe that poſſeſt 'em;</l>
                  <l>The plate ſtood next, I'me Iure.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhake I ſhake Boy, what a cold ſweat—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>This may worke, what will become on's ſir?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                  <l>She is cold, dead cold: de'e find' your conſcience,</l>
                  <l>De'e bring your Gillians hither—nay, ſhee's puniſh'd,</l>
                  <l>Your conceal'd love's caſ'd up?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis <hi>Maria,</hi> the very ſame, the Bride, new horror.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                  <l>Theſe are fine tricks, you hope ſhee's in a ſound,</l>
                  <l>But Ile take order ſhe ſhall ne'r recover</l>
                  <l>To bore my noſe, come, take her up and bury her</l>
                  <l>Quickly, or Ile cry out; take her up inſtantly.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Be not ſo haſty foole, that may undoe us;</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:14"/>
                  <l>We may be in for murther ſo; be patient,</l>
                  <l>Thou ſeeſt ſhe's dead, and cannot injure thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                  <l>I am ſure ſhe ſhall not.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Be not ſir dejected,</l>
                  <l>Too much a ſtrange miſtake! this had not been elſe,</l>
                  <l>It makes me almoſt weep to think upon't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>What an unluckie theef am I?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile no conſidering, either beſtir your ſelf, or—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Hold.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                  <l>Let it not ſtay, to ſmell then, I will not</l>
                  <l>Indure the ſtink of a Rival.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Would twere there agen.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>We muſt bury her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>But where o'th ſudden, or with what providence,</l>
                  <l>That no eyes watch us.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                  <l>Take a Spade and follow me,</l>
                  <l>The next fair ground we meet, make the Church-yard;</l>
                  <l>As I live, Ile ſee her lodg'd. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>It muſt be ſo,</l>
                  <l>How heavy my heart is, I ha no life left.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>I am paſt thinking too, no underſtanding,</l>
                  <l>That I ſhould miſſe the right Cheſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>The happy Cheſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>That, which I ſaw and markt too.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Well paſſion wo'not help us,</l>
                  <l>Had I twenty fals for this?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy,</speaker>
                  <l>Twas my fault ſir.</l>
                  <l>And twenty thouſand fears for this, oth'devil,</l>
                  <l>Now could I curſe, well, we have her now,</l>
                  <l>And muſt diſpoſe her.
<stage>Enter Miſtreſſe.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                  <l>Hang both for two blind buzzards, here's a Spade</l>
                  <l>Quickly or Ile call the neighbours.</l>
                  <l>There's no remedy,</l>
                  <l>Would the poor hung<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y priſoners had this paſtie. <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                     <stage>Enter Iuſtice, and a Servant with a light.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>Twas a ſtrange miſchance ſir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>Miſchance, ſaiſt? No twas happineſſe to me,</l>
                  <l>There's ſo much charge ſav'd, I have her portion,</l>
                  <l>Ile marry twenty more on ſuch conditions.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>Did it not trouble you ſir,</l>
                  <l>To ſee her dead?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb facs="tcp:46367:14"/>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>Not much, I thank my conſcience;</l>
                  <l>I was tormented till that happen'd, furies</l>
                  <l>Were in my brain to think my ſelf a Cuckold</l>
                  <l>At that time of the night:</l>
                  <l>When I come home, I charge you ſhut my doors,</l>
                  <l>Locks, bolts, and barres, are little enough to ſecure me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, and pleaſe you?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>Fool to ask that queſtion;</l>
                  <l>To keep out women, I expect her mother</l>
                  <l>Will viſit me with her clamors, oh I hate</l>
                  <l>Their noiſe, and do abhorre the whole ſex heartily;</l>
                  <l>They are all walking Devils, Harpyes, I will ſtudy</l>
                  <l>A week together how to raile ſufficiently,</l>
                  <l>Upon e'm all, and that I may be furniſh'd,</l>
                  <l>Thou ſhalt buy all the railing Books and Ballads,</l>
                  <l>That Malice hath invented againſt women,</l>
                  <l>I will read nothing elſe, and practiſe 'em,</l>
                  <l>Till I grow fat with curſes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>If youle go</l>
                  <l>To th'charge, let me alone to find you Books.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>They come neer us.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>Whats that?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>Where? hold up the Torch Knave.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>Did you hear nothing, 'tis a—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>Why doſt make a ſtand?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>Whats that?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>Where, where, doſt ſee any thing?</l>
                  <l>We are hard by the Church-yard, and I was never</l>
                  <l>Valiant at midnight in ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ch i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>kſome places;</l>
                  <l>They ſay Ghoſts walk ſometimes, hark, de'e hear nothing?</l>
                  <stage>Enter Lurcher, Boy <hi>and</hi> Miſtreſſe.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                  <l>No further, dig here, and lay her in quickly.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>VVhat light is that Boy, we ſhall be diſcover'd;</l>
                  <l>Set the Coffin up an end, and get behind me,</l>
                  <l>There's no avoiding.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>VVhere's that groan? I begin to be afraid.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>VVhat ſhall we do ſir?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>VVe are almoſt at home now, thou muſt go forward;</l>
                  <l>Perhaps 'twas my imagination.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis he?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>I know him too, let me alone.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh ſir, a Ghoſt, the very Ghoſt of Miſtreſſe B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ide,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:15"/>
                  <l>I have no power to runne away.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>Curſed Ghoſt, bleſſe me, preſerve me,</l>
                  <l>I doe command thee what ſo ere thou art,</l>
                  <l>I doe conjure thee leave me; doe not fright me;</l>
                  <l>If thou beeſt a divell vexe me not ſo ſoone,</l>
                  <l>If thou beeſt</l>
                  <l>The ſpirit of my wife.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy</speaker>
                  <l>Thy wife.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhall be tormented.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Thy abus'd wife, that cannot peaceably</l>
                  <l>Enjoy her death, thou haſt an evill conſcience.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ju.</speaker>
                  <l>Ikow it</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Among thy other ſinnes which blacke thy ſoule,</l>
                  <l>Call to thy minde thy vow made to another,</l>
                  <l>Whom thou haſt wrong'd, and make her ſatisfaction</l>
                  <l>Now I am dead, thou perjur'd man, or elſe</l>
                  <l>A thouſand black tormentors ſhall purſue thee,</l>
                  <l>Vntill thou leape into eternall flames;</l>
                  <l>Where gold which thou adoreſt here on earth</l>
                  <l>Melted, the Fiends ſhall powre into thy throate;</l>
                  <l>For this time paſſe; goe home and thinke upon me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Away.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>There are more ſpirits.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>Thanke you deare wife,</l>
                  <l>Ile beſtow twentie nobles of a Tombe for thee,</l>
                  <l>Thou ſhalt not walke and catch cold after death.
<stage>They goe Backward in.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>So, ſo, they'r gone, twas my ingenious raſcal:</l>
                  <l>But how doſt know he made vowes to another?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>I over-heard the women talke to night on't;</l>
                  <l>But now lets loſe no time ſir, pray lets bury</l>
                  <l>This Gen lewoman, where's my Miſtreſſe? <stage>Enter Miſtreſſe.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                  <l>Here I durſt not tarry.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>we ha ſo coſen'd the old forty i'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h hundred,</l>
                  <l>And the devill hinder him not, hee'le goe a pilgrimage;</l>
                  <l>But come, about our buſineſſe, ſet her downe agen.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Shee groanes, ha.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar</speaker>
                  <l>Oh!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Agen, ſhe ſtirres.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                  <l>Lets fly, or elſe we ſhall be torne in peeces.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>And you be good at that, bury your ſelfe,</l>
                  <l>Or let the Sexton take ye for his fee,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:15"/>
                  <l>Away boy. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>I am very cold, dead cold;</l>
                  <l>Where am I? What's this? a Coffin? where have I been?</l>
                  <l>Mercy defend me: Ha, I doe remember</l>
                  <l>I was betrai'd, and ſwounded; my heart akes,</l>
                  <l>I am wondrous hungry too, dead bodies eate not;</l>
                  <l>Sure I was meant for buriall, I am frozen;</l>
                  <l>Death, 'like a cake of Ice dwells round about me,</l>
                  <l>Darkneſſe ſpreads o're the world too, where? what path?</l>
                  <l>Beſt providence direct me. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <head>Actus Tertius.</head>
               <stage>Enter Lady, Wildbraine, Women, Toby,</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>THou art the moſt unfortunate fellow;</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>Why Aunt what have I done?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>The moſt malicious varlet,</l>
                  <l>Thy wicked head never at reſt, but hammering,</l>
                  <l>And haching h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lliſh things, and to no purpoſe,</l>
                  <l>So thou maiſt have thy baſe will.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Why doe you raile thus?</l>
                  <l>Cannot a ſcurvy accident fall out,</l>
                  <l>But I muſt be at one end on't?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou art at both ends.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Cannot young ſullen wenches play the fools,</l>
                  <l>And marry, and die, but I muſt be the agent?</l>
                  <l>All that I did (and if that be an injury,</l>
                  <l>Let the world judge it) was but to perſwade her,</l>
                  <l>(And as I take it) I was bound to it too,</l>
                  <l>To make the reverend coxecombe her husband Cuckold:</l>
                  <l>What elſe could I adviſe her, was there harme i' this?</l>
                  <l>You are of yeares, and have runne through experience,</l>
                  <l>Would you be content if you were young agen,</l>
                  <l>To have a continuall cough grow to your pillow,</l>
                  <l>A rottenneſſe, that vaults are perfumes to</l>
                  <l>Hang in youre roofe, and like a fogge infect you;</l>
                  <l>Anointed hammes to keepe his hinges turning</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:16"/>
                  <l>Reck ever in your noſe, and twenty night caps,</l>
                  <l>With twenty ſeveral ſweats.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>Some Jew, ſome Juſtice,</l>
                  <l>A thouſand heathen ſmels to ſay truth Madam,</l>
                  <l>And would you mellow my young pretty Miſtreſſe</l>
                  <l>In ſuch a miſ-ken?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Sirra,</l>
                  <l>Where's the body of my Girle?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>I know not,</l>
                  <l>I am no Conjurer, you may look the body,</l>
                  <l>I was like to be ſtoln away my ſelf, the Spirit</l>
                  <l>Had like to ha ſurpris'd me in the ſhape of a woman,</l>
                  <l>Of a young woman, and you know thoſe are dangerous.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>So had I Madam, ſimply though I ſtand here,</l>
                  <l>I had been raviſh'd too: I had twenty Spirits</l>
                  <l>In every corner of the houſe a Fiend met me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>You lie like raskals,</l>
                  <l>Was Miſtreſſe <hi>Newlove</hi> ſuch a Spirit ſir</l>
                  <l>To fright your worſhip;</l>
                  <l>Well, I diſcharge you ſir, ye'are now at libertie,</l>
                  <l>Live where you pleaſe, and do what pranks you fancy,</l>
                  <l>You know your ſubſtance, though you are my Nephew,</l>
                  <l>I am no way bound ſir to protect your miſchief;</l>
                  <l>So fare you well.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Farewell good Aunt, I thank you,</l>
                  <l>Adi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w honeſt <hi>Nick,</hi> the devil if he have power,</l>
                  <l>Will perſecute your old bones, for this marriage,</l>
                  <l>Farewel Miſtreſſe <hi>Win.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>And ſhall we part with dry lips;</l>
                  <l>Shall we that have been fellow devils together</l>
                  <l>Flench for an old womans fart?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis a fine time a night too, but we muſt part <hi>Nick.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>Shall we never ring again? ne're toſſe the tenor,</l>
                  <l>And roul the changes in a Cup of Claret?</l>
                  <l>You ſhall not want what ere I lay my hands on,</l>
                  <l>As I am ſure <hi>Automedon</hi> the Coachman,</l>
                  <l>Shall be diſtributed; bear up, I ſay, hang ſorrow,</l>
                  <l>Give me that bird abroad that lives at pleaſure,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sam</hi> the Butle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s true, the Cook a reverend Trojan,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:16"/>
                  <l>The Faulkner ſhall ſell his Hawkes, and ſwear they were rotten,</l>
                  <l>There be ſome wandring ſpoons, that may be met with,</l>
                  <l>Ile pawn a Coach horſe, peace, utter no ſentences.</l>
                  <l>The harneſſe ſhall be us'd in our warres alſo;</l>
                  <l>Or ſhall I drive her) tell me but your will now,</l>
                  <l>Say but the word) over ſome rotten bridg,</l>
                  <l>Or by a Marle pit ſide, ſhe may ſlip in daintily,</l>
                  <l>Let me alone for my ſelf.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>No, no, farewel <hi>Toby,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Farewel ſpinie <hi>Nicholas,</hi> no ſuch thing,</l>
                  <l>There be wayes i'the world, if you ſee me</l>
                  <l>A day or two hence, may be weel'le crack a quart yet,</l>
                  <l>And pull a bell, commend to the houſhold;</l>
                  <l>Nay, cry not <hi>Toby</hi> 'twill make thy head giddy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>Sweet Maſter <hi>Wildbrain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>No more <hi>Toby,</hi> go, the times may alter—</l>
                  <l>But where's the coarſe of my dead coſen,</l>
                  <l>(If ſhe be dead) I hop'd 'thad but diſſembled</l>
                  <l>That ſits heavy here: <hi>Toby,</hi> honeſt <hi>Toby,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Lend me thy Lanthorn, I forgot 'twas dark,</l>
                  <l>I had need look to my wayes now.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>Take a lodging with me to night in the Stable,</l>
                  <l>And ride away to morrow with one of the horſes</l>
                  <l>Next your heart, pray do.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>No, good night good neighbour <hi>Toby,</hi> I will wander,</l>
                  <l>I ſcorn to ſubmit my ſelf, ere I have rambled,</l>
                  <l>But whether, or with what, that's more material;</l>
                  <l>No matter, and the worſt come it is but ſtealing,</l>
                  <l>And my Aunt won'ot ſee me hang'd for her own credit,</l>
                  <l>And farewel in a halter coſts me nothing. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     <stage>Enter Hartlove.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>The night, and all the evils the night covers,</l>
                  <l>The Goblins, Hagges, and the black ſpawne of darkneſſe,</l>
                  <l>Cannot fright me, no death, I dare thy cruelty.</l>
                  <l>For I am weary both of life and light too;</l>
                  <l>Keep my wits heaven, they ſay ſpirits appear</l>
                  <l>To melancholly minds, and the graves open,</l>
                  <l>I would fain ſee the fair <hi>Maria</hi>'s ſhadow,</l>
                  <l>But ſpeak unto her ſpirit ere I dyed,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:17"/>
                  <l>But ask upon my knees a mercy from her;</l>
                  <l>I was a villain, but her wretched Kinſman,</l>
                  <l>That ſet his plot, ſhall with his heart blood ſatisfie</l>
                  <l>Her injur'd life and honor, what lights this?
<stage>Enter Wildbrain with a Lanthorn.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>It is but melancholy walking thus;</l>
                  <l>The Tavern doors are baracado'd too,</l>
                  <l>Where I might drink till morn in expectation;</l>
                  <l>I cannot meet the Watch neither; nothing in</l>
                  <l>The likeneſſe of Conſtable, whom I might</l>
                  <l>In my diſtreſſe abuſe, and ſo be carried,</l>
                  <l>For want of other lodging, to the Counter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis his voyce, Fate, I thanke thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha, who's that, and thou beeſt a man ſpeak?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Franke Heartlove,</hi> then I bear my deſtinies,</l>
                  <l>Thou art the man of all the world I wiſh'd for;</l>
                  <l>My Aunt has turn'd me out a doores, ſhe has,</l>
                  <l>At this unchriſtian houre, and I doe walke,</l>
                  <l>Me thinks, like <hi>Guido Faux</hi> with my darke Lanthorn,</l>
                  <l>Stealing to ſet the towne a fire; ith' country</l>
                  <l>I ſhould be tane for William o' the Wiſpe,</l>
                  <l>Or Robin Good fellow, and how doſt <hi>Frank?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>The worſe for you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Come, thar'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a foole, art going to thy lodging?</l>
                  <l>Ile lie with thee to night, and tell thee ſtories,</l>
                  <l>How many devills we ha met withal;</l>
                  <l>Our houſe is haunted <hi>Franke,</hi> whole legions,</l>
                  <l>I ſaw fiftie for my ſhare.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Didſt not fright e'm?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>How, fright e'm? no they frighted me fufficiently.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou hadſt wickedneſſe enough to make them ſtare,</l>
                  <l>And be afraid o'thee, malicious devil;</l>
                  <l>And draw thy ſword, for by <hi>Marias</hi> ſoule;</l>
                  <l>I will not let thee ſcape to do more miſchiefe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou art mad, what doſt meane?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>To kill thee, nothing elſe will eaſe my anger,</l>
                  <l>The injury is freſh, I bleede with all,</l>
                  <l>Nor can that word expreſſe it, there's no peace in't,</l>
                  <l>Nor muſt it be forgiven but in death;</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:17"/>
                  <l>Therefore call up thy valour if thou'ſt any,</l>
                  <l>And ſummon up thy ſpirits to defend thee;</l>
                  <l>Thy heart muſt ſuffer for thy damn'd practiſes,</l>
                  <l>Againſt thy noble coſen, and my innocence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Hold, heare a word; did I doe any thing</l>
                  <l>But for your good, that you might have her,</l>
                  <l>That in that deſperate time I might redeeme her,</l>
                  <l>Although with ſhew of loſſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Out ugly villaine,</l>
                  <l>Fling on her the moſt hated name of Whore</l>
                  <l>To the worlds eye, and face it out in courteſie,</l>
                  <l>Bring him to ſee't and make me drunke to attempt it.
<stage>Enter Maria.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <l>I heare ſome voyces this way.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>No more, if you can pray, doe it as you fight.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <l>What new frights oppoſe me? I have heard that tongue.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis my fortune,</l>
                  <l>You could not take me in a better time ſir,</l>
                  <l>I ha nothing to loſe, but the love I lent thee,</l>
                  <l>My life my ſword protect.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <l>I know'em both, but to prevent their ruines,</l>
                  <l>Muſt not diſcover—ſtay men moſt deſperate;</l>
                  <l>The miſchiefe you are forward to commit</l>
                  <l>Will keepe me from my grave, and tie my ſpirit</l>
                  <l>To endleſſe troubles elſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha, tis her Ghoſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Maria.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <l>Heare me both, each wound you make</l>
                  <l>Runnes through my ſoule, and is a new death to me,</l>
                  <l>Each threatning danger will affright my reſt;</l>
                  <l>Looke on me <hi>Hartlove,</hi> and my kinſman view me;</l>
                  <l>Was I not late in my unhappy marriage,</l>
                  <l>Sufficient miſerable? full of all misfortunes?</l>
                  <l>But you muſt adde with your moſt impious angers</l>
                  <l>Unto my ſleeping duſt this inſolence?</l>
                  <l>Would you teach time to ſpeake eternally</l>
                  <l>Of my diſgraces; make Records to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eep'em,</l>
                  <l>Keep them in braſs? fight then, and kill my honor;</l>
                  <l>Fight deadly both, and let your bloody ſwords,</l>
                  <l>Through my reviv'd, and reeking infamy</l>
                  <l>(That never ſhall be purg'd) finde your owne ruines:</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:18"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hartlove,</hi> I lov'd thee once, and hop'd again</l>
                  <l>In a more bleſſed love to meet thy ſpirit,</l>
                  <l>If thou kil'ſt him, thou art a murtherer,</l>
                  <l>And murther ſhall never inherit heaven:</l>
                  <l>My time is come, my concealed grave expects me,</l>
                  <l>Farewel, and follow not, your feet are bloody,</l>
                  <l>And will pollute my peace: I hope they are melted,</l>
                  <l>This is my way ſure. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Stay bleſſed ſoul.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>VVould ſhe had come ſooner, and ha ſav'd ſome blood.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Doſt bleed?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes certainly, I can both ſee and feel it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Now I well hope it is not dangerous;</l>
                  <l>Give me thy hand, as honor guides me,</l>
                  <l>Ile know thee again. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>I thank thee heartily;</l>
                  <l>I know not where to get a Surgeon;</l>
                  <l>This viſion troubles me, ſure ſhe is living,</l>
                  <l>And I was fooliſh blind, I could not find it;</l>
                  <l>I bleed apace ſtill, and my heart grows heavy,</l>
                  <l>If I go far I faint, Ile knock at this houſe,</l>
                  <l>They may be charitable, would t'were perfect day.
<stage>Enter Miſtreſſe.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis not he? What would you ſir?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>I would crave a little reſt Lady,</l>
                  <l>And for my hurts ſome Surgerie, I am a Gentleman</l>
                  <l>That Fortune of a fight—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                  <l>A handſome Gentleman,</l>
                  <l>Alas he bleeds, a very handſome Gentleman,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>A ſweet young wench, beſhrow my heart a fair one;</l>
                  <l>Fortune has made me ſome recompence,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                  <l>Pray come in; the air is hurtful for you</l>
                  <l>Pray let me lead you, Ile have a bed for you preſently,</l>
                  <l>Ile be your Surgeon too, alas ſweet Gentleman.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>I feel no hurts, the morning comes too faſt now.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                  <l>Soſtly I beſeech you. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     <stage>Enter Lady and Toby.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>He is not up yet Madam, what mean't you</l>
                  <l>To come forth ſo early?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>You block head;</l>
                  <l>Yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r eyes are ſow'd up ſtill, they cannot ſee</l>
                  <l>When it is day: oh my poor <hi>Maria;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:18"/>
                  <l>Where be the women?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>They ſaid they would follow us.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>He ſhall not laugh thus at my miſery,</l>
                  <l>And kill my child, and ſteal away her body,</l>
                  <l>And keep her Portion too.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>Let him be hang'd for't,</l>
                  <l>You have my voice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Theſe women not come yet?</l>
                  <l>A ſonne in law, Ile keep a Conjurer,</l>
                  <l>But Ile find out his knavery.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>Do, and Ile help him.</l>
                  <l>And if he were here this whip ſhould conjure him,</l>
                  <l>Here's a capias, and it catch hold on's breech,</l>
                  <l>Ide make him ſoon beleeve the Devil were there.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>An old Uſurer.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>He married the mony, thats all he lookt for,</l>
                  <l>For your daughter, let her ſink or ſwim.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile ſwim him;</l>
                  <l>This is his houſe, I wonder they ſtay thus,</l>
                  <l>That we might raiſe him out on's wits.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>They'le come,</l>
                  <l>Fear not Madam, and bring clappers with 'em</l>
                  <l>Or ſome have loſt their old wont, I have heard</l>
                  <l>No diſparagement to your Ladiſhip, ſome o'their tongues</l>
                  <l>Like Tom a Lincolne three miles off.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh fie,</l>
                  <l>How tedious are they?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>What and we loſt no time,</l>
                  <l>You and I ſhall make a ſhift to begin with him,</l>
                  <l>And tune our Inſtruments, till the conſort come</l>
                  <l>To make up the full noiſe, Ile knock.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>Who's that? rapt ſo ſawcily?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis I, <hi>Toby,</hi> come down, or elſe we'le fetch you down,</l>
                  <l>Alas, this is but the Sauncebell, here's a Gentlewoman</l>
                  <l>Will ring you another peal, come down, I ſay.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>Some new fortifications, look to my doors,</l>
                  <l>Put double barres, I will not have her enter,</l>
                  <l>Nor any of her Tribe, they come to terrefie me:</l>
                  <l>Keep out her tongue too if you can.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>I hear you,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:19"/>
                  <l>And I will ſend my tongue up to your worſhip,</l>
                  <l>The Eccho of it ſhall flye o're the ſtreete;</l>
                  <l>My Daughter, that thou killedſt with kindneſſe (Jew)</l>
                  <l>That thou betrayedſt to death, thou double Jew,</l>
                  <l>And after ſtol'ſt her body.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>Iew's too good for him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>I defie you both;</l>
                  <l>Thy daughter plaid the villaine and betray'd me:</l>
                  <l>Betray'd my honor.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Honor, Raſcal,</l>
                  <l>And let that bear an action, Ile try it with thee,</l>
                  <l>Honor?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh Reprobate!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou muſtie Iuſtice,</l>
                  <l>Buy an honourable halter, and hang thy ſelfe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>A worſhipful ropes end is too good for him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Get honor that way, thou wot die a dogge elſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>Come and be whipt firſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Where is her Portion. <stage>Enter Nurſe and women.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>Where Ile keepe it ſafely.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>Traitor, thou ſhalt not keep it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>More of the kennel? put more bolts to'th doores there,</l>
                  <l>And arme your ſelves, hell is broke looſe upon us.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>I am glad y'are come, weele blow the houſe down.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh Nurſe, I haue ſuch cauſe—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wo.</speaker>
                  <l>Villaine, viper, although you had no cauſe, we are bound</l>
                  <l>To helpe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, and beleeve, we come not here to examine,</l>
                  <l>And if you pleaſe weele fire the houſe</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>Call the Conſtable.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>A charitable motion, fire is comfortable.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>No no, wele only let him know ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> minds,</l>
                  <l>We will commit no outrage, he's a Lawyer,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>Give me my musket.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Where's my daughters body,</l>
                  <l>That I may bury it?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wo.</speaker>
                  <l>Speak, or weele bury thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>Alive weele bury thee, ſpeak old Iniquitie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>Bury him alive by all meanes for a teſtimony.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>Their voyces make my houſe reel, oh for Officers,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:19"/>
                  <l>I am in a dreame, thy daughters ſpirit</l>
                  <l>Walkes a nights, and troubles all the neighbours;</l>
                  <l>Goe hire a Conjurer, Ile ſay no more.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>The Law ſhall ſay more,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wo. Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>We are witneſſes,</l>
                  <l>And if thou beeſt not hang'd—
<stage>Enter Lurcher, and Boy.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Buy a book of good manners,</l>
                  <l>A ſhort Book of good manners.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Buy a ballad, a ballad of the maid was got with child</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>That might ha beene my caſe laſt night,</l>
                  <l>Ile ha't what ere it coſt me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy</speaker>
                  <l>A ballad of the witches hang'd at Ludlow.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>I will have that too;</l>
                  <l>There was an Aunt of mine, I thinke amongſt e'm,</l>
                  <l>I would be glad to heare her Teſtament.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>A new book of women,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>The thunders laid, how they ſtare at him</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>A new book of fooles, a ſtrange book,</l>
                  <l>Very ſtrange fooles.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile owe thee a good turne what e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'e thou art.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>A book of walking ſpirits.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>That I like not.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>Nor I, they walk'd me the fooles morris.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>A book of wicked women.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>Thats well thought on.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Of rude malicious women, of proud women,</l>
                  <l>Of ſcolding, women, we ſhall nere get in.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>A ballad of wrong'd Maides.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile buy that.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>A little very little book.</l>
                  <l>Of good and godly women, a very little one,</l>
                  <l>So little, you may put it in a nutſhel.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>with a ſmall print, that no body can read it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>Peace ſirra, or Ile teare your books.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>Open the doore, and let him in, I love him</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>A book of evil Magiſtrates.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>I marry, dee hear that Juſtice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>And their eviller wives,</l>
                  <l>That weare their places in their peticotes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb facs="tcp:46367:20"/>Ju.</speaker>
                  <l>Dee you hear that Lady.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>A book new printed, againſt Playing,</l>
                  <l>Dancing, Masking, May-poles; a zealous Brothers book,</l>
                  <l>And full of Fables.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Another book of women, of mad women,</l>
                  <l>Women that were born in March. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Are you got in?</l>
                  <l>We would ha pul'd your knaves hide elſe; this fellow</l>
                  <l>Was ſent to abuſe us, but we ſhall have time</l>
                  <l>To talk more with this Juſtice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ju.</speaker>
                  <l>Farewel Madam, as you like this come viſit me agen,</l>
                  <l>You and your treble ſtrings, now ſcold your hearts out—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wo.</speaker>
                  <l>Shall he carry it thus away?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>Go to the Judg, and what you'le have us ſwear—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>I thank ye heartily,</l>
                  <l>Ile keep that for the laſt, I will go home,</l>
                  <l>And leave him to his Conſcience for a while,</l>
                  <l>If it ſleep long, Ile wake it with a vengeance. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     <stage>Enter Servants.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1.</speaker>
                  <l>What book has he given thee?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2.</speaker>
                  <l>A dainty book, a book of the great Navy,</l>
                  <l>Of fifteen hundred ſhips of Canon proof,</l>
                  <l>Built upon Whales to keep their keels from ſinking;</l>
                  <l>And Dragons in'em, that ſpit fire ten mile;</l>
                  <l>And Elephants that carry goodly caſtles.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1.</speaker>
                  <l>Doſt thou beleeve it?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2.</speaker>
                  <l>Shall we not beleeve books in Print?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1.</speaker>
                  <l>I have <hi>John Taylors</hi> book of Hempſeed too,</l>
                  <l>Which for two lines I hapned on by chance,</l>
                  <l>I reverence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2.</speaker>
                  <l>I prethee what are they?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1.</speaker>
                  <l>They are ſo put upon the time, as if</l>
                  <l>He ſtudied to anſwer the late Hiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iomaſtix,</l>
                  <l>Talking of change and transformations,</l>
                  <l>That wittily, and learnedly he bangs him,</l>
                  <l>So many a Puritans ruffe, though ſtarched in Print,</l>
                  <l>Be turn'd to Paper, and a Play writ in't:</l>
                  <l>A Play in the Puritans ruf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e? Ile buy his Works for't,</l>
                  <l>And conſute <hi>Horace</hi> with a Water Poet:</l>
                  <l>What haſt there a ballad too?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:20"/>
                  <speaker>2.</speaker>
                  <l>This is a pecce of Poetry indeed;
<stage>He ſings; Juſtice cries within.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>What noiſe is that?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1.</speaker>
                  <l>Some cry ith' ſtreets; prethee ſing on. <stage>Sing again.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2.</speaker>
                  <l>Agen, doſt not hear? 'tis ith' houſe certainly?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis a ſtrange noiſe? and has a tang o'the Juſtice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2.</speaker>
                  <l>Lets ſee? <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Enter the Servants bringing in their Maſter bound and gag'd.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1.</speaker>
                  <l>Untie his feet, pull out his gag, he will choak elſe;</l>
                  <l>What deſperate rogues were theſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2.</speaker>
                  <l>Give him freſh air.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ju.</speaker>
                  <l>I will never ſtudy books more;</l>
                  <l>I am undone, theſe villains have undone me.</l>
                  <l>Rifled my Desk, they have undone me learnedly;</l>
                  <l>A fire take all their books, Ile burn my Study:</l>
                  <l>Where were you raſcals when the villains bound me,</l>
                  <l>You could not hear.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1.</speaker>
                  <l>He gave us books ſir, dainty books to buſie us;</l>
                  <l>And we were reading in that which was the Brewhouſe;</l>
                  <l>A great way off, we were ſinging ballads too,</l>
                  <l>And could not hear.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ju.</speaker>
                  <l>This was a precious theef,</l>
                  <l>A ſubtle trick to keep my ſervants ſafe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2.</speaker>
                  <l>What ha you loſt ſir?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ju.</speaker>
                  <l>They ranſack'd all before my face, and threatned</l>
                  <l>To kill me, if I congh'd, they have a chain,</l>
                  <l>My rings, my box of caſting gold, my pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe too,</l>
                  <l>They rob'd me miſerably; but that which moſt grieves me,</l>
                  <l>They took away ſome writings; twas a Rogue</l>
                  <l>That knew me, and ſet on by the old Lady,</l>
                  <l>I will indite her for't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1.</speaker>
                  <l>Shall we purſue 'em?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ju.</speaker>
                  <l>Run, run, curſed raskals,</l>
                  <l>I am out of my wits, let not a creature in,</l>
                  <l>No not with neceſſaries.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2.</speaker>
                  <l>We ſhall be ſtarv'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ju.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile buy my meat at window, as they paſſe by;</l>
                  <l>I wonot truſt my Scrivenor, he has books too;</l>
                  <l>And bread Ile ha ſlung up; I charge ye all</l>
                  <l>Burn all the books i'th houſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1.</speaker>
                  <l>Your little Prayer book?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb facs="tcp:46367:21"/>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile never pray agen, ile have my doores</l>
                  <l>Made up, nothing but walls, and thicke ones too;</l>
                  <l>No ſound ſhall tempt me a gen, remember I</l>
                  <l>Have for ſwoare bookes,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2.</speaker>
                  <l>If you ſhould be call'd to take your oath.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>I will forſwear all oaths, rather than ſee</l>
                  <l>A thing but in the likeneſſe of a booke:</l>
                  <l>And I were condemn'd, Ile rather chuſe to hang,</l>
                  <l>Than read agen; come in, and ſearch all places,</l>
                  <l>They may be about the houſe, were the doores lock'd?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1.</speaker>
                  <l>But the keyes in 'em, and if they be gone,</l>
                  <l>They could not want wit to lock us in ſir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>Never was man ſo miſerably undone,</l>
                  <l>I would loſe a limbe to ſee their rogueſhips totter. <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                     <stage>Enter Lady and Nurſe.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Thy brothers daughter, ſaiſt, and born in Wales?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>I have long time deſired to ſee her, and I hope</l>
                  <l>Your Ladiſhip will not be offended.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>No, no.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhould be happy if ſhe might be ſerviceable</l>
                  <l>To you Madam.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Beſhrow me, but at firſt, ſhe took me much,</l>
                  <l>Is ſhe not like <hi>Maria?</hi> ſetting aſide</l>
                  <l>Her language very like her, and I love her</l>
                  <l>The better for't, I prethee call her hither,</l>
                  <l>She ſpeakes feat Engliſh.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>Why <hi>Guennith, Guennith, du hummah Guenneth;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>She is courſe Madam, after her country guiſe,</l>
                  <l>And were ſhe in fine clothes—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile have her handſome: <stage>Enter Maria.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>What part of Wales were you borne in?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <l>In Abehundis Madams.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>She ſpeakes that name in Welſh, which we call Breck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocke</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>What can you do?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Her was toe many tings in Walls, know not the faſhion in Londons? her was milk the Cowes, make ſeeze and butters, and ſpinne very well the Welſh freeze, her was Cooke to te Mountain cots, and ſing very fine prittiſh tunes was mage good ales and breds, and her know to dance on Sundayes, marge you now Madams.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb facs="tcp:46367:21"/>La.</speaker>
                  <l>A pretty innocence, I doe like her infinitely, <hi>Nurſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And if I live— <stage>Enter Servant.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>Here is Mr. <hi>Hartlove,</hi> Madam come to ſee you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas poore Gentleman, prethee admit him.
<stage>Enter Hartlove and Gent.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, I am come to take my laſt leave.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>How ſir?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>Of all my home affections, and my friends,</l>
                  <l>For the intereſt you had once in <hi>Maria,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cquaint you when I leave the kingdome.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Would there were any thing in my poore power</l>
                  <l>That might divert your will, and make you happy;</l>
                  <l>I am ſure I haue wrong'd her too, but let your pardon</l>
                  <l>Aſſure me you are charitable; ſhee's dead</l>
                  <l>Which makes us both ſad: What do you look on?</l>
                  <l>The likeſt face—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Pleſſe us awle, why does that ſentilman make ſuch unders and mazements at her, I know her not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>Be not offended maid.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>How the Wench bluſhes, ſhee repreſents <hi>Marias</hi> loſſe to him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Will the ſentilman hurt her, pray you be her defences, was haue mad phiſnomies, is her troubled with Lunaticks in her praine pans, bleſſe us awle.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>Where had you this face?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <l>Her faces be our none I warrant her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha,</speaker>
                  <l>I wonot hurt you, all the lineaments</l>
                  <l>That built <hi>Maria</hi> up; all thoſe ſpringing beauties</l>
                  <l>Dwell on this thing, change but her tongue I know her:</l>
                  <l>Let me ſee your hand.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Du Guin, was never theeves, and robberies; here is no ſindge in her hands warrant her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>Truſt me, the ſelf-ſame white,</l>
                  <l>And ſoftneſſe, prethee ſpeak our Engliſh Dialect.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Haleggs? what does her ſpeage hard urds to her, to make poore <hi>Guennith</hi> ridicles, was no mannerly ſentilman to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe her</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>By the love,</l>
                  <l>That everlaſting love I bare <hi>Maria</hi>—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb facs="tcp:46367:22"/>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Maria,</hi> her name was <hi>Guenith,</hi> and good names, was poore elſe, oman maide, her have no fine kanags to madge her trickſie, yet in her owne cuntries was held a fine enſe her can tels her, and honeſt enſe too, marg you dat now, her can keepe her little legges cloſe enough warrant her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>How pretily this anger ſhewes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1.</speaker>
                  <l>She gabbles innocently.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam farewell, and all good fortune dwell w'ee,</l>
                  <l>With me my owne affections; farwell maid,</l>
                  <l>Faire gentle maide.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2</speaker>
                  <l>She ſighes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <l>Du cat a whee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>I cannot goe, theres ſomwhat calls me backe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <l>Poore <hi>Franke,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>How gladly would I entertaine thy love,</l>
                  <l>And meet thy worthy flame, but ſhame forbids, me:</l>
                  <p>If pleaſe her Ladyſhip dwell here with <hi>Guenneth,</hi> and learne to ſpinne and card ull, to mage flannells, and linſeyes ulſeis, ſall tawgco'd urds to her Ladyſhips urſhips for her.
<stage>The teares flow from him,</stage>
                  </p>
                  <l>The teares of true affection, woe is me,</l>
                  <l>O curſed love that glories in maids miſeries,</l>
                  <l>And true mens broken hearts.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas I pitty him, the wench is rude, and knowes you not, forgive her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Wyne your nyes pray you, though was porne in Walls 'mong craggy rocks, and mountaines yet heart is ſoft, looke you, hur can weepe too, when hur ſee men mage prinie teares and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>How hard ſhe holds me?</l>
                  <l>Juſt as <hi>Maria</hi> did, weepes the ſame drops,</l>
                  <l>Now as I have a living ſoule, her ſight too;</l>
                  <l>What ſhall I thinke, is not your name <hi>Maria,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If it be not, delude me with ſo much charity</l>
                  <l>To ſay it is.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Vpon her life, you was mightie deal in love with ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>odies, your pale ſeekes and hollow nyes, and pantings upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er poſome, know very well, becauſe looke you, her thinke her honeſt ſentilman, you ſall call her <hi>Maria.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>Good Madam, thinke not ill I am thus ſawcie,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb facs="tcp:46367:22"/>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh no ſir, be you not angry with the wench.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>I am moſt pleas'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1.</speaker>
                  <l>Lets interrupt him, hee'l be mad outright elſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2.</speaker>
                  <l>Obſerve a little more.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>Would I could in your language beg a kiſſe,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>If her have neceſſities of a kiſſe, looke you, dere is one in ſarities.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>Let me ſuffer death,</l>
                  <l>If in my apprehenſion two twinnd cherries</l>
                  <l>Be more a kin, then her lips to <hi>Marias;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And if this harſh illuſion would but leave her,</l>
                  <l>She were the ſame, good Madam, ſhall I have</l>
                  <l>Your conſent now.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>To what?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>To give this Virgin to me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>She's not mine, this is her Kinſwoman,</l>
                  <l>And has more power to diſpoſe; alas, I pitty him.</l>
                  <l>Pray gentleman prevaile with him to goe;</l>
                  <l>More that I wiſh his comfort than his abſence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>You have beene alwayes kind to me, will you</l>
                  <l>Denie me your faire Couſen.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nu.</speaker>
                  <l>'Twere fit you firſt obtain'd her own conſent.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>He is no friende that wiſhes my departure,</l>
                  <l>I doe not trouble you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis not <hi>Maria.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>Her ſhadow is enough, Ile dwell with that,</l>
                  <l>Perſue your owne wayes, ſhall we live together;</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>If her will come tomorrow and tauge to her, her will tell her more of her meanings, and then if her be melancholy, her will ſing her a Welch ſong too, to make her merries, but <hi>Guenith</hi> was very honeſt; her was never love but one ſentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and he was beare her great teale of goodills too, was marry one day S. <hi>Davy</hi> her give her five paire of white gloves, if her will dance at her weddings.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>All I am worth,</l>
                  <l>And all my hopes, this ſtrange voyce would forſake her,</l>
                  <l>For then ſhe ſhud be—prethee ſtay a little,</l>
                  <l>Harke in thine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>are, diſſemble not, but tell me,</l>
                  <l>And ſave my life; I know you are <hi>Maria:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Speke but as) doe ten words to confirme me;</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:23"/>
                  <l>You have an Engliſh ſoule, do not diſguiſe it</l>
                  <l>From me with theſe ſtrange accents—She pinch'd hard</l>
                  <l>Againe, and ſigh'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>What ailes the Wench? <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, <hi>Gunith.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>She's gone too,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2.</speaker>
                  <l>Come leave this dreame.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha</speaker>
                  <l>A dreame? I thinke ſo;</l>
                  <l>But 'twas a pleaſing one, now Ile obey,</l>
                  <l>And forget all theſe wonders, lead the way. <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <head>Actus Quartus.</head>
               <stage>Enter Wildbrain and Toby.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>HOneſt <hi>Toby?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>Sweet Mr. <hi>Wildbrain,</hi>—I am glad I ha met we yee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Why did my aunt ſend for me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Aunt's a mortal, and thinkes not on you</l>
                  <l>For ought I can perceive.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Is my Coſen alive agen?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>Neither, and yet we doe not heare</l>
                  <l>That ſhe's buried.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>What ſhould make thee glad then?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>What ſhould make me glad? have I not cauſe,</l>
                  <l>To ſee your Princely body well, and waike thus,</l>
                  <l>Looke blith and bonny, and your wardrobe whole ſtill?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>The Caſe is cleare, and I ha found a Mine;</l>
                  <l>A perfect Indie, ſince my Aunt caſheer'd me;</l>
                  <l>What think'ſts of this?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh delicate bells.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou putteſt me in minde,</l>
                  <l>We are to ring anon, I mean to ſend for thee;</l>
                  <l>Meere me at the old Pariſh Church.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>Say no more.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>When thy Lady is a bed, we ha conſpir'd</l>
                  <l>A midnight peale for joy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb facs="tcp:46367:23"/>To.</speaker>
                  <l>If I faile hang mei'th bell ropes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>And how? and how does my Aunt?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To</speaker>
                  <l>She's up to'th eares in Law;</l>
                  <l>I doe ſo whirle her to the Counſellors chambers,</l>
                  <l>And backe againe, and bounce her for more money,</l>
                  <l>And too again, I know not what they doe with her;</l>
                  <l>But ſhe's the merrieſt thing among theſe Lawdrivers;</l>
                  <l>And in their ſtudies halfe a day together;</l>
                  <l>If they doe get her with <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> ſhe ſweares,</l>
                  <l>By all the abilitie of her old body,</l>
                  <l>She will ſo claw the Juſtice, ſhe will ſell</l>
                  <l>The tiles of the houſe ſhe vowes, and ſacke out o'th cellar,</l>
                  <l>(That ſhe worſhips to Idolatry) but ſhele hang him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>I would ſhe could: but hark thee honeſt <hi>Toby.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If a man haue a Miſtreſſe, may we not</l>
                  <l>With out my Aunts leave, borrow now and then</l>
                  <l>A coach to tumble in, toward the Exchange,</l>
                  <l>And ſo forth?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>A Miſtreſſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>She may be thine when we are married.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>Command, Ile carry you both in pompe;</l>
                  <l>And let my Lady go a foot a Law-catching,</l>
                  <l>And exerciſe her cornes: where is ſhe Maſter <hi>Iohn?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Shat ſee her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>Shall we ring for her?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>And drinke her health.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>Drinke ſtiffely for five hours.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Weele drinke fifteen.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>To night? we will ha twenty torches then,</l>
                  <l>And through the ſtreet drive on triumphantly;</l>
                  <l>Triumphantly weele drive, by my Ladyes doore,</l>
                  <l>As I am a Chriſtian, Coachman, I will rattle you</l>
                  <l>And urine in her porch and ſhe ſhall feare me:</l>
                  <l>If you ſay more, I ſhall runne mad outright,</l>
                  <l>I will drinke ſack and ſurfeit inſtantly;</l>
                  <l>I know not where I am now. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <stage>Enter Lurcher.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Hold for thy buttons ſake, the knave's tranſported.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jacke Wildbraine?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Honeſt <hi>Tom,</hi> how thrives the fellonious world with thee now?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb facs="tcp:46367:24"/>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>You looky and talke as you were much exalted.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>That't i'th right <hi>Tom.</hi> Ile tell thee firſt,</l>
                  <l>I ha ſhooke off my Aunt, and yet I live ſtill,</l>
                  <l>And drink, and ſing; her houſe had like to ha ſpoil'd me;</l>
                  <l>I keepe no houres now;</l>
                  <l>Nor need any falſe key</l>
                  <l>To the old womans Cabinets, I ha money</l>
                  <l>Vpon my word, and pawne no oathes toth' Buttler;</l>
                  <l>No matrimoniall proteſtations</l>
                  <l>For ſacke poſſets to the chambermaid,</l>
                  <l>I praiſe my Fate, there be more wayes toth' wood <hi>Tom.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Prethee releaſe my wonder.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile encreaſe it, wipe thine eyes,</l>
                  <l>Here is a chaine worth mony and ſome man had it,</l>
                  <l>A fooliſh Diamond, and other trifles—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>The very ſame, Oh Gipſey! Infidell!</l>
                  <l>All that I ſweat, and ventur'd my necke for,</l>
                  <l>He has got already; who would truſt a ſtrumpet.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>This? This is nothing to what I poſſeſſe</l>
                  <l>At home.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>What home?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>A houſe that ſhall be nameleſſe;</l>
                  <l>The Miſtreſſe of it mine too, ſuch a peece</l>
                  <l>For fleſh and blood, added to that ſo loving—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Is ſhe married?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>I know not, nor I care not;</l>
                  <l>But ſuch a prize, ſo mounting, ſo delicious,</l>
                  <l>Thou wilt runne mad, Ile tell thee more hereafter,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tur.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay prethee a word more.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>I tooke no paines to finde out all this Paradiſe,</l>
                  <l>My deſtiny threw me upon't ith' darke, I found it</l>
                  <l>Wanting a lodging too.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>No old acquaintance?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Never, never ſaw her;</l>
                  <l>But theſe things happen not in every age,</l>
                  <l>I cannot ſtay, If thou wilt meete anon</l>
                  <l>At my owne randevow, thou knoweſt the Tavern,</l>
                  <l>Weele ſup together, after that a company</l>
                  <l>Of mery lads have made a match to ring.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>You keepe youre exerciſe, i'the old Church?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb facs="tcp:46367:24"/>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>No other,</l>
                  <l>There is no muſicke to the bells, we wo'd</l>
                  <l>Have bonefires if we durſt, and thou wo'd come</l>
                  <l>It ſhall coſt thee nothing <hi>Tom,</hi> hang pilfering,</l>
                  <l>And keepe me company, in time I may</l>
                  <l>Shew thee my Wench too.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>I cannot promiſe; but you will be there?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Weele toſſe the bells, and make the ſteeple</l>
                  <l>Rore boy, but come to ſupper then.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>My hand, and expect me:</l>
                  <l>Yes I will come or ſend, and to ſome purpoſe;</l>
                  <l>Art come boy?</l>
                  <stage>Enter Boy with Gowne, Beard, and Conſtables ſtaffe.</stage>
                  <l>Excellent, Knave, how didſt thou purchaſe theſe?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy</speaker>
                  <l>The ſtaffe I ſtole laſt night from a ſleeping Conſtable;</l>
                  <l>The reſt I borrowed by my acquaintance with</l>
                  <l>The players boyes; you were beſt to loſe no time ſir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>So, ſo, helpe boy, tis very well, doe I not looke</l>
                  <l>Like one that breakes the Kings peace with authoritie?</l>
                  <l>You know your charge, prepare things hanſomely,</l>
                  <l>My diligent boy, and leave me to my office,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>There wants nothing already; but I fly ſir. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Now Fortune prove no ſlut, and Ile adore thee.</l>
                  <stage>Within.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>Whoſe there? <stage>Knocks.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>A friend wo'd ſpeake with Maſter Juſtice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>Who are you?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>I am the Conſtable.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>My Maſter is not at leaſure to heare buſineſſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>How? Not at leaſure to doe the King ſervice;</l>
                  <l>Take heede what you ſay ſir; I know his worſhip,</l>
                  <l>If he know my buſineſſe, would no excuſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>You muſt goe to another Juſtice, Ile aſſure</l>
                  <l>My Maſter is not well in health.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>I know not,</l>
                  <l>But if your worſhipful be not at leaſure</l>
                  <l>To do himſelfe a benefit, I am gone ſir,</l>
                  <l>An infinite benefit, and the State ſhall thanke him for't;</l>
                  <l>Thanke him, and thinke on him too; I am an Officer,</l>
                  <l>And know my place, but I doe love the Juſtice;</l>
                  <l>I honor any authoritie above me:</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:25"/>
                  <l>Beſide, he is my neighbour, and I worſhip him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>You have no bookes, not ballads, Mr Conſtable,</l>
                  <l>About you?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>What ſhould I doe with bookes? does it become</l>
                  <l>A man of my place to underſtand ſuch matters?</l>
                  <l>Pray call your Maſter, if he pleaſe to follow me,</l>
                  <l>I ſhall diſcover to him ſuch a plot,</l>
                  <l>Shall get him everlaſting fame, Ile be hang'd for't</l>
                  <l>And he be not knighted inſtantly, and for reward</l>
                  <l>Have ſome of the malefactors lands Ile bring him too;</l>
                  <l>But I can not delay time. <stage>Within.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>Who's that?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>A Conſtable ſir, would ſpeake about ſome buſineſſe,</l>
                  <l>He ſayes, will bring you fame, and mighty profit.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Pleaſe your worſhip, come downe, Ile make you happy;</l>
                  <l>The notabl'ſt peece of villany I have in hand ſir,</l>
                  <l>And you ſhall finde it out; I ha made choyce</l>
                  <l>To bring your worſhip to the firſt knowledge, and</l>
                  <l>Thanke me, as you finde the good on't afterwards.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>What is it? Treaſon?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis little better, I can tell you, I have lodg'd.</l>
                  <l>A crew of the moſt rank and deſperate villaines:</l>
                  <l>They talke of robberies, and wayes they did'em;</l>
                  <l>And how they left men bound in their ſtudies.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>With bookes and ballads?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>That ſir? that, and murders,</l>
                  <l>And thouſand knaveries more, tha'te very rich ſir,</l>
                  <l>In mony, jewels, chaines, and a hundered more</l>
                  <l>Devices.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>Happy, happy Conſtable, I met yee</l>
                  <l>At the back doore, get ready knaves.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Not a man I beſeech you,</l>
                  <l>I have privately appointed ſtrength about me,</l>
                  <l>They cannot ſtart, your men would breede ſuſpition;</l>
                  <l>All my deſire is you would come alone;</l>
                  <l>That you might have the hope of the enterpriſe,</l>
                  <l>That you might heare e'm firſt, and then proceed ſir,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>I come, I come.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis very well. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb facs="tcp:46367:25"/>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>Keep all my doors faſt, 'tis ſomething late.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>So, ſo, and pleaſe your worſhip I direct you. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <stage>Enter Boy.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>My Maſter ſtayes, I doubt his lime-twigges catch not,</l>
                  <l>If they do, all's provided; but I all</l>
                  <l>This while forget my own ſtate, fair <hi>Maria</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is certainly alive, I met her in</l>
                  <l>Another habit, with her Nurſe, 'twas ſhe:</l>
                  <l>There is ſome trick in't, but when this is over,</l>
                  <l>Ile find it out, this project for the Uſurer</l>
                  <l>May have good effect; however 'twill be ſport</l>
                  <l>To mortifie him a litle; <stage>Enter Lurcher.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>He's come without him:</l>
                  <l>Have you fail'd ſir?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Proſper'd? my little Ingineer; away,</l>
                  <l>He is ith' next room, be not you ſeen, ſirra. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>The pitfall's ready, never Juſtice</l>
                  <l>Was caught in ſuch a nooze, ere he get out,</l>
                  <l>He ſhall run through a ſcouring purgatory,</l>
                  <l>Shall purge him to the quick, 'tis night already. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <stage>Enter Algripe and Lurcher.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Come ſoftly, yet ſir ſoftly, are you not weary?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>Th'aſt brought me into a melancholy place,</l>
                  <l>I ſee no creature.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>This is, ſir, their den</l>
                  <l>Where they ſuppoſe themſelves ſecure, I am faint,</l>
                  <l>With making haſt; but I muſt be thus troubled,</l>
                  <l>And therefore never go without a cordial; <stage>Seems to drink.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Without this I ſhould die;</l>
                  <l>How it refreſhes me</l>
                  <l>Already? will't pleaſe your worſhip? I might have had</l>
                  <l>The manners to ha let you drink before me;</l>
                  <l>Now am I Iuſty.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>'Twas a good taſte.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Taſte? how dee find the vertue, nay ſir ſpare it not:</l>
                  <l>My wife has the receit, do's it not ſtir</l>
                  <l>Your worſhips body? when you come to examine,</l>
                  <l>'Twill make you ſpeak like thunder</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>Hoy he.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>I works already.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>Is there never a chair, I was wearier than I thought,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:26"/>
                  <l>But who ſhall we have to take 'em Mr. Conſtable?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Let me alone, when I but give the watch-word</l>
                  <l>We will have men enough to ſurpriſe an Army.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ju.</speaker>
                  <l>I begin to be ſleepy; what, haſt a chair?</l>
                  <stage>Enter another with a chair.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>They do not dream of us, 'tis early riſing;</l>
                  <l>Care, care, and early riſing, common-wealths men</l>
                  <l>Are ever ſubjects to the nods; ſitdown ſir,</l>
                  <l>A ſhort nap is not much amiſs; ſo, ſo, he's faſt;</l>
                  <l>Faſt as a fiſh ith' net, he has winking powder</l>
                  <l>Shall work upon him to our wiſh, remove him,</l>
                  <l>Nay, we may cut him into collops now</l>
                  <l>And he n're feel; have you prepar'd the vault ſirra?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, yes, ſir, every thing in's place.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>When we have plac'd him, you and I boy</l>
                  <l>Muſt about another project hard by, his potion</l>
                  <l>Will bind him ſure enough till we return,</l>
                  <l>This villany weighs mainly, but weele purge ye. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <stage>Bells ring.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Sexton.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sex.</speaker>
                  <l>Now for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ears, mine ears be conſtant to me;</l>
                  <l>They ring a wager, and I muſt deal juſtly, ha boyes.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Lurcher and Boy.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Doſt hear'em, ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d, theſe be the Ringers?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Are you ſure the fame?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Or my directions fail;</l>
                  <l>The coaſt is clear:</l>
                  <l>How the bells go? how daintily they tumble?</l>
                  <l>And me thinks they ſeem to ſay; Fine fools Ile fit you?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sex.</speaker>
                  <l>excellent agen, good boyes—oh that was nought.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Who's that? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Be you conce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>'d by any means yet; hark,</l>
                  <l>They ſtop, I hope thei'le to'o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gon, cloſe ſir.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Wildbrain, Toby, Ringers.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>A palpable knock.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rin.</speaker>
                  <l>'Twas none.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>Be judg'd by the Sexton then,</l>
                  <l>If I have ears.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sex.</speaker>
                  <l>A knock, a knock, a groſs one.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>Carman your gallon of wine, you ring moſt impiouſly,</l>
                  <l>Art thou of the worſhipful company of the Knights oth' Weſt,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:26"/>
                  <l>And handle a bell with no more dexterity;</l>
                  <l>You think you are in Thames ſtreet</l>
                  <l>Juſtling the carts: oh a clean hand's a jewel.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Good ſpeed to your good exerciſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>Y'are welcome.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>I come ſir from a Gentleman, and neighbour hard by,</l>
                  <l>One that loves your muſick well.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>He may have more on't,</l>
                  <l>Handle a bell, as you were haling timber;</l>
                  <l>Groſs, groſs, and baſe, abſurd,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rin.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile mend it next peal.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>To intreat a knowledge of you, whether it be</l>
                  <l>By the Ear you ring thus cunningly or by the Eye;</l>
                  <l>For to be plain, he has laid ten pounds upon't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>But which way has he laid?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>That your Ear guides you,</l>
                  <l>And not your Eye.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>Has won, has won, the Ear's our onely inſtrument:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>But how ſhall we be ſure on't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>Put all the lights out, to what end ſerve our Eyes then?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>A plain Caſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſay true, 'tis a fine cunning thing to ring by th'ear ſure:</l>
                  <l>And can you ring ith' dark ſo?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>All night long boy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis wonderful, let this be certain Gentlemen,</l>
                  <l>And half his wager he allows among ye;</l>
                  <l>Iſt poſſible you ſhould ring ſo?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>Poſſible. thou art a child, Ile ring when I am dead drunk</l>
                  <l>Out with the lights, no twinckling of a candle,</l>
                  <l>I know my rope too, as I know my noſe,</l>
                  <l>And can bang it ſoundly ith' dark, I warrant you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Come let's confirm him ſtraight and win the wager. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Let me hear to ſtrengthen me;</l>
                  <l>And when y'ave rung Ile bring the money to you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>So, ſo, follow'em;</l>
                  <l>They ſhall have a cool reward, one hath gold of mine,</l>
                  <l>Good ſtore in's pocket, <stage>Ring.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>But this will be reveng'd in a ſhort warning.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:27"/>
                  <l>They are at it luſtily; hey, how wantonly</l>
                  <l>They ring away their cloaths, how it delights me;</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Here, here, ſir.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Boy with cloaths.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Haſt <hi>Wildbraines.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>His whole caſe ſir; I felt it out, and by the guards</l>
                  <l>This ſhould be the Coachmans, another ſuite too.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Away Boy, quickly now to the Uſurer,</l>
                  <l>His hour to wake approaches.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>That once finiſh'd,</l>
                  <l>Youle give me leave to play ſir: here they come.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Wildbrain, Toby, and Ringers.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>I am monſtrous weary.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>Fie, how I ſwear? Reach me my cloak to cover me,</l>
                  <l>I run to oyl like a Porpiſe; 'twas a brave peal.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sex.</speaker>
                  <l>Let me light my candle firſt, then Ile wait on you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>A very brave peal.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>Carman, you came in cloſe now.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Sure 'tis paſt midnight.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rin.</speaker>
                  <l>No ſtirring in the ſtreets I hear.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>Walk further, was that a pillar? 'tis harder than my noſe.</l>
                  <l>Where's the Boy promis'd us five pound?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Room, I ſweat ſtill; come, come, my cloak,</l>
                  <l>I ſhall take cold.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Sexton.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sex.</speaker>
                  <l>Where lies it?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Here, here, and all our cloaths.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sex.</speaker>
                  <l>Where, where?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rin.</speaker>
                  <l>Ith' the corner.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>Is thy candle blind too, give me the bottle,</l>
                  <l>I can drink like a Fiſh now, like an Elephant.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sex.</speaker>
                  <l>Here are the corners, but here are no cloaths;</l>
                  <l>Yes, here is a cuffe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>A cuffe? give me the candle,</l>
                  <l>Cuffes wo'not cover me—I ſmell the knavery.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>Iſt come to a cuffe? my whole ſuit turned to a button?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Now am I as cold again as though 'twere Chriſtmas;</l>
                  <l>Cold with my fear, Ile never ring by the ear more.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>My new cloaths vaniſh'd?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>My all cloaths <hi>Toby.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rin.</speaker>
                  <l>Here's none.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>Not one of my dragons wings left to adorn me,</l>
                  <l>Have I muted all my feathers?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb facs="tcp:46367:27"/>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Cheated by the ear; a plot to put out the candle;</l>
                  <l>I could be mad; my chain, my rings, the gold, the gold.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>The cold, the cold I cry, and I cry truly,</l>
                  <l>Not one ſleeve, nor a cape of a cloak to warm me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>What miſerable fools were we?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>We had e'en beſt, gentlemen,</l>
                  <l>Every man chuſe his rope again, and faſten it,</l>
                  <l>And take a ſhort turn to a better fortune</l>
                  <l>To be bawds to our miſeries, and put our own lights out?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Prethee Sexton lets have a fire at thy houſe,</l>
                  <l>A good fire, weele pay thee ſome way for't, I am ſtone cold.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sex.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas I pitty you, come quickly Gentlemen.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Sure I ha been in a dream, I had no Miſtreſs,</l>
                  <l>Nor gold, nor cloaths, but am a ringing raſcal.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>Fellows in affliction, let's take hands all,</l>
                  <l>Now are we fit for tumblers.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Lurcher and others, bringing in Algripe.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>So, ſo, preſently his ſleep will leave him.</l>
                  <l>And wonder ſeize upon him,</l>
                  <l>Bid 'em within be ready.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ju.</speaker>
                  <l>What ſound's this?</l>
                  <l>What horrid dinne? what diſmal place is this?</l>
                  <l>I never ſaw before, and now behold it;</l>
                  <l>But by the half light of a lamp, that burns here:</l>
                  <l>My ſpirits ſhake, tremble through my body;</l>
                  <l>Help, help,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Enter two Furies with black tapers.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Mercy, protect me, my ſoul quakes,</l>
                  <l>What dreadful apparitions! how I ſhudder!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1. 2. Fu.</speaker>
                  <l>Algripe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ju.</speaker>
                  <l>What are you?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1.</speaker>
                  <l>We are helhounds, helhounds, that have commiſſion From the Prince of darkneſs,</l>
                  <l>To fetch thy black ſoul to him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ju.</speaker>
                  <l>Am I not alive ſtill?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou art, but we have brought thee inſtruments</l>
                  <l>Will quickly rid thy miſerable life, Stabbe,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2.</speaker>
                  <l>Poyſon.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1.</speaker>
                  <l>Hang thy ſelf, this choiſe is offer'd,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou canſt not hope for heaven; thy baſe ſoul is Loſt to all hope of mercy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2.</speaker>
                  <l>Quickly, quickly,</l>
                  <l>The torments cool.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1.</speaker>
                  <l>And all the Fiends expect thee.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:28"/>
                  <l>Come with us to that pit of endleſs horrour,</l>
                  <l>Or we will force thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ju.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh, oh, oh.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1.</speaker>
                  <l>Groans are too late, ſooner the raviſher,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſoul is hurl'd into eternal froſt,</l>
                  <l>Stung with the force of twenty thouſand Winters,</l>
                  <l>To puniſh the diſtempers of his blood,</l>
                  <l>Shall hope to get from thence, then thou avoid</l>
                  <l>The certainty of meeting hell where he is.</l>
                  <l>Shall murderers be there for ever dying,</l>
                  <l>Their ſouls ſhot through with adders, torn on Engines,</l>
                  <l>Dying as many deaths for killing one,</l>
                  <l>Could any imagination number them,</l>
                  <l>As there be moments in eternity:</l>
                  <l>And ſhall that Juſtice ſpare thee, that haſt ſlain,</l>
                  <l>Murdered by thy extortion ſo many?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ju.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh, oh.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2.</speaker>
                  <l>Do execution quickly, or we'le carry thee alive to hell.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ju.</speaker>
                  <l>Gently, gentle devils, do not force me</l>
                  <l>To kill my ſelf, nor do not you do't for me;</l>
                  <l>O let me live, Ile make amends for all.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1.</speaker>
                  <l>Tell us of thy repentance? perjur'd villain,</l>
                  <l>Pinch off his fleſh, he muſt be whipt, ſalted and whipt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ju.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh miſery of miſeries!</l>
                  <stage>Recorders</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1. 2.</speaker>
                  <l>Tear his accurſed limbs, to hell with him, ha.</l>
                  <l>A miſchief on that innocent face, away.</l>
                  <stage>Creeps in</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Boy like an Angel.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Malicious furies hence, choak not the ſeeds</l>
                  <l>Of holy penitence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ju.</speaker>
                  <l>This muſt be an Angel,</l>
                  <l>How at his preſence the fiends crawle away?</l>
                  <l>Here is ſome light of mercy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Be thou wiſe,</l>
                  <l>And entertain it, wretched, wretched man;</l>
                  <l>What poor defence hath all thy wealth been to thee?</l>
                  <l>What ſayes thy conſcience now?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>Be my good Angel, here I promiſe thee,</l>
                  <l>To become honeſt, and renounce all villany;</l>
                  <l>Enjoyn me any pennance, Ile build Churches;</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:28"/>
                  <l>A whole City of Hoſpitals.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Take heed,</l>
                  <l>There is no dallying, nor are theſe impos'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>Name any thing within my power, ſweet Angel;</l>
                  <l>And if I do not faithfully perform it,</l>
                  <l>Then whip me every day, burn me each minute,</l>
                  <l>Whole years together let me freeze to Iſicles.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Ith' number of thy foul oppreſſions;</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt undone a faithful Gentleman,</l>
                  <l>By taking forfeit of his land.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>Young <hi>Lurcher,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I do confeſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>He lives moſt miſerable,</l>
                  <l>And in deſpair may hang or drown himſelf;</l>
                  <l>Prevent his ruine, or his blood will be</l>
                  <l>More ſin in thy account: haſt thou forgotten</l>
                  <l>He had a ſiſter?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>I do well remember it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Couldſt thou for Mammon break thy ſolemn vow,</l>
                  <l>Made once to that unhappy maid, that weeps</l>
                  <l>A thouſands tears a day for thy unkindneſs,</l>
                  <l>Was not thy faith contracted, and thy heart?</l>
                  <l>And couldſt thou marry another?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>But ſhe is dead,</l>
                  <l>And I will make true ſatisfaction.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>What do inſtance theſe, that haſt been falſe</l>
                  <l>To all the world.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>I know it, and will henceforth</l>
                  <l>Practiſe repentance, do not ſrown ſweet Angel;</l>
                  <l>I will reſtore all morgages, forſwear</l>
                  <l>Abominable Uſury, live chaſte;</l>
                  <l>For I have been wanton in my ſhroud, my age;</l>
                  <l>And if that poor innocent maid, I ſo abus'd,</l>
                  <l>Be living, I will marry her, and ſpend</l>
                  <l>My dayes to come religiouſly.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>I was commanded but a Meſſenger</l>
                  <l>To tell thee this, and reſcue thee from thoſe,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe malice would have drag'd thee quick to hell,</l>
                  <l>If thou abuſe this mercy and repent nor,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:29"/>
                  <l>Double damnation will expect thee for it;</l>
                  <l>But if thy life be vertuous hereafter,</l>
                  <l>A bleſſedneſs ſhall reward thy good example,</l>
                  <l>Thy fright hath much diſtracted thy weak ſenſes,</l>
                  <l>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ink of this viol, and renew thy ſpirits,</l>
                  <l>I ha done my office, think on't and be happy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>So, ſo, he gapes already, now he's faſt;</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt acted rarely; but this is not all;</l>
                  <l>Firſt, help to convey him out o'th vault.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>You will diſpenſe with me now, as you promis'd ſir,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>We will make ſhift without thee, tha'ſt done well,</l>
                  <l>By our device this bondage may ſcape hell.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Lady, Nurſe, Maria.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Didſt think <hi>Maria,</hi> this poor outſide, and</l>
                  <l>Diſſembling of thy voice could hide thee from</l>
                  <l>A mothers ſearching eye, though too much fear,</l>
                  <l>Leſt thou wert not the ſame, might blind a lover</l>
                  <l>That thought thee dead too; oh my dear <hi>Maria,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I hardly Kept my joyes in from betraying thee:</l>
                  <l>VVelcome again to life, we ſhall find out</l>
                  <l>The myſtery of thy abſence; conceale</l>
                  <l>Thy perſon ſtill, for <hi>Algripe</hi> muſt not know thee:</l>
                  <l>And exerciſe this pretty dialect;</l>
                  <l>If there be any courſe in Law to free thee,</l>
                  <l>Thou ſhalt not be ſo miſerable; be ſilent</l>
                  <l>Good Nurſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſhall not need to fear me Madam,</l>
                  <l>I do not love the uſuring Jew ſo well;</l>
                  <l>Beſide, 'twas my trick to diſguiſe her ſo.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Be not dejected <hi>Mall.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <l>Your care may comfort me;</l>
                  <l>But I deſpair of happineſs:</l>
                  <stage>Hartlove,</stage>
                  <l>I dare not ſee him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>VVeele withdraw.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhall but grieve to ſee his paſſions too,</l>
                  <l>Since there's no poſſibility to relieve him.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Hartlove.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>The world's a Labyrinth, where unguided men</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:29"/>
                  <l>Walk up and down to find their wearineſs;</l>
                  <l>No ſooner have we meaſured with much toil</l>
                  <l>One crooked path, with hope to gain our freedom,</l>
                  <l>But it betrays us to a new affliction;</l>
                  <l>What a ſtrange mockery will man become</l>
                  <l>Shortly to all the creatures?</l>
                  <l>Oh <hi>Mariah!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If thou beeſt dead, why does thy ſhadow fright me?</l>
                  <l>Sure 'tis becauſe I live; were I but certain</l>
                  <l>To meet thee in one grave, and that our duſt</l>
                  <l>Might have the priuiledge to mix in ſilence,</l>
                  <l>How quickly ſhould my ſoul ſhake off this burthen!</l>
                  <stage>Enter Boy.</stage>
                  <l>Thus far my wiſhes have ſucceſs, Ile loſe</l>
                  <l>No time: Sir, are not you call'd Mr. <hi>Hartlove?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Pardon my rudeneſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>What does that concern</l>
                  <l>Thee Boy, 'tis a name cannot advantage thee,</l>
                  <l>And I am weary on't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Had you conceal'd,</l>
                  <l>Or I forgot it ſir, ſo large were my</l>
                  <l>Directions, that you could not ſpeak this language,</l>
                  <l>But I ſhould know you by your ſorrow.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou</l>
                  <l>Wert well inform'd, it ſeems; well, what's your buſineſe?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>I come to bring you comfort.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>Is <hi>Maria</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Alive agen? that's ſomewhat, and yet not</l>
                  <l>Enough to make my expectation riſe, to</l>
                  <l>Paſt half a bleſſing, ſince we cannot meet</l>
                  <l>To make it up a full one; th'art miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aken.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>VVhen you have heard me, you'le think otherwiſe:</l>
                  <l>In vain I ſhould report <hi>Maria</hi> living:</l>
                  <l>The comfort that I bring you muſt depend</l>
                  <l>Upon her death.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'art a diſſembling boy,</l>
                  <l>Some one has ſent thee to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>k me, though my anger</l>
                  <l>Stoop <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> to puniſh thy green years, unripe</l>
                  <l>For malice did I know what perſon ſent thee</l>
                  <l>To tempt my ſorrow thus, I ſhould revenge it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb facs="tcp:46367:30"/>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Indeed I have no thought ſo uncharitable,</l>
                  <l>Nor am I ſent to grieve you, let me ſuffer</l>
                  <l>More puniſhment than ever boy deſerv'd,</l>
                  <l>If you do find me falſe; I ſerve a Miſtreſs</l>
                  <l>VVould rather dye than play with your misfortunes;</l>
                  <l>Then good ſir hear me out.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>VVho is your Miſtreſs?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Before I name her, give me ſome incouragement,</l>
                  <l>That you receive her meſſage, ſhe is one</l>
                  <l>That is full acquainted with your miſery,</l>
                  <l>And can bring ſuch a portion of her ſorrow</l>
                  <l>In every circumſtance ſo like your own,</l>
                  <l>You'le love and pity her, and wiſh your griefs</l>
                  <l>Might marry one anothers.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou art wild?</l>
                  <l>Canſt thou bring comfort from ſo ſad a creature?</l>
                  <l>Her miſerable ſtory can at beſt,</l>
                  <l>But ſwell my Volume, large enough already.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>She was late belov'd, as you were, promis'd faith,</l>
                  <l>And marriage, and was worthy of a better</l>
                  <l>Than he, that ſtole <hi>Maria's</hi> heart.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>How's that?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Juſt as <hi>Maria</hi> dealt with your affection,</l>
                  <l>Did he that married her, deal with my Miſtreſs,</l>
                  <l>VVhen careleſs both of honour and Religion;</l>
                  <l>They cruelly gave away their hearts to ſtrangers,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>Part of this truth I Know, but prethee boy</l>
                  <l>Proceed to that thou cam'ſt for; thou didſt promiſe</l>
                  <l>Something, thy language cannot hitherto</l>
                  <l>Encourage me to hope for.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>That I come to:</l>
                  <l>My miſtreſs thus unkindly dealt with all,</l>
                  <l>You may imagine, wanted no affliction;</l>
                  <l>And had ere this, Wept her ſelf drye as marble,</l>
                  <l>Had not your fortune come to her relief,</l>
                  <l>And twinne to her own ſorrow brought her comfort.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>Could the condition of my fate ſo equal,</l>
                  <l>Leſſen her ſufferings?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb facs="tcp:46367:30"/>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>I know not how</l>
                  <l>Companions in grief ſometimes diminiſh</l>
                  <l>And make the preſſure eaſie, by degrees:</l>
                  <l>She threw her troubles off, remembring yours,</l>
                  <l>And from her pity of your wrongs, there grew</l>
                  <l>Affection to your perſon thus increas'd,</l>
                  <l>And with it, confidence, that thoſe whom Nature</l>
                  <l>Had made ſo even in their weight of ſorrow,</l>
                  <l>Could not but love as equally one another,</l>
                  <l>Were things but well prepar'd, this gave her boldneſs</l>
                  <l>To employ me thus far.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>A ſtrange meſſage boy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>If you incline to meet my Miſtreſs love,</l>
                  <l>It may beget your comforts; beſides that,</l>
                  <l>'Tis ſome revenge, that you above their ſcorn</l>
                  <l>And pride, can laugh at them, whoſe perjury</l>
                  <l>Hath made you happy, and undone themſelves.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>Have you done boy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Onely this little more:</l>
                  <l>When you but ſee, and know my Miſtreſs well,</l>
                  <l>You will forgive my tediouſneſs, ſhe's fair,</l>
                  <l>Fair as <hi>Maria</hi> was.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile hear no more,</l>
                  <l>Go fooliſh Boy, and tell thy fonder Miſtreſs</l>
                  <l>She has no ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cond Faith to give away;</l>
                  <l>And mine, was given to <hi>Maria,</hi> though her death</l>
                  <l>Allow me freedom, ſee the Picture of her.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Maria, Nurſe.</stage>
                  <l>I would give ten thouſand Empires for the ſubſtance;</l>
                  <l>Yet for <hi>Maria's</hi> ſake, whoſe divine Figure</l>
                  <l>That rude frame carries, I will love this counterfeit</l>
                  <l>Above all the world, and had had thy Miſtreſs all</l>
                  <l>The grace and bloſſom of her ſex; now ſhe</l>
                  <l>Is gone, that was walking a Spring of beauty,</l>
                  <l>I would not look upon her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, your pardon,</l>
                  <l>I have but done a meſſage, as becomes</l>
                  <l>A ſervant, nor did ſhe on whoſe commands</l>
                  <l>I gladly waited, bid me urge her love</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:31"/>
                  <l>To your diſquiet, ſhe wouldchide my diligence</l>
                  <l>If I ſhould make you angry.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>Bretty Boy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Indeed I fear I have offended you:</l>
                  <l>Pray if I have, enjoyn me any pennance for it;</l>
                  <l>I have perform'd one duty, and could as willingly</l>
                  <l>To purge my fault, and ſhew I ſuffer with you,</l>
                  <l>Plead your cauſe to another.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>And Ile take thee</l>
                  <l>At thy word boy, thou haſt a moving language,</l>
                  <l>That pretty innocent, Copie of <hi>Maria</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is all I love, I know not how to ſpeak,</l>
                  <l>Winne her to think well of me, and I will.</l>
                  <l>Reward thee to thy wiſhes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>I undertake</l>
                  <l>Nothing for gain, but ſince you have reſolv'd.</l>
                  <l>To love no other, Ile be faithful to you,</l>
                  <l>And my propheticke thoughts bid me already</l>
                  <l>Say I ſhall proſper.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou wert ſent to bleſs me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Pray give us opportunity.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>Be happy.</l>
                  <stage>Exit:</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>He's gone.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>With your fair leave Miſtreſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <l>Have you buſineſs with her pray you?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>I have a meſſage from a gentleman,</l>
                  <l>Pleaſe you vouchſafe your ear more private.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſhall have my abſence Neece.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <p>Was the ſentleman afeard to declare his matters openly, here was no bodies was not very honeſt, if her like not her er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rands the petter, was wiſt to keep her preathes to coole her por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridges, can tell her that now for aule her private hearings and tawgings.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>You may, if pleaſe you, find another language,</l>
                  <l>And with leſs pains be underſtood.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <l>What is her meaning?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Come, pray ſpeak your own Engliſh.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <l>Have boyes loſt her itts and memories? bleſs us aule.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>I muſt be plain then, come, I know you are</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maria,</speaker>
                  <l>this thinne vail cannot obſcure you:</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:31"/>
                  <l>Ile tell the world you live, I have not loſt yee,</l>
                  <l>Since firſt with griefe and ſhame to be ſurpris'd,</l>
                  <l>A violent trance took away ſhew of life;</l>
                  <l>I could diſcover by what accident</l>
                  <l>You were convey'd away at midnight, in</l>
                  <l>Your coffin, could declare the place, and minute,</l>
                  <l>When you reviv'd, and what you have done ſince as perfectly—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas, I am betraid to new misfortunes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>You are not for my knowledge, Ile be dumbe</l>
                  <l>For ever, rather than be ſuch a traytor;</l>
                  <l>Indeed I pity you, and bring no thoughts,</l>
                  <l>But full of peace, call home your modeſt blood,</l>
                  <l>Pale hath too long uſurp'd upon your face;</l>
                  <l>Think upon love agen, and the poſſeſſion</l>
                  <l>Of full blown joyes, now ready to ſalute you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <l>Theſe words undo me more than my own griefes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſee how fear would play the tyrant with you,</l>
                  <l>But Ile remove ſuſpition; have you in</l>
                  <l>Your heart an entertainment for his love,</l>
                  <l>To whom your Virgin faith made the firſt promiſe?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <l>If thou mean'ſt <hi>Hartlove,</hi> thou doſt wound me ſtill,</l>
                  <l>I have no life without his memory,</l>
                  <l>Nor with it any hope to keep it long,</l>
                  <l>Thou ſeeſt I walk in darkneſs like a theef,</l>
                  <l>That fears to ſee the world in his own ſhape,</l>
                  <l>My very ſhadow frights me, tis a death</l>
                  <l>To live thus, and not look day in the face,</l>
                  <l>Away, I know thee not.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſhall hereafter Know, and thank me Lady,</l>
                  <l>Ile bring you a diſcharge at my next viſit,</l>
                  <l>Of all your fears, be content fair <hi>Maria,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Tis worth your wonder.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <l>Impoſſible.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Be wiſe and ſilent,</l>
                  <l>Dreſs your ſelf, you ſhall be what you wish.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <l>Do this, and be</l>
                  <l>My better Angell.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>All your cares on me.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <pb facs="tcp:46367:32"/>
               <head>Actus Quintus.</head>
               <stage>Enter Lurch. and Boy.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>I Muſt applaud thy diligence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>It had been nothing</l>
                  <l>To have left him in the Porch; I cal'd his ſervants,</l>
                  <l>With wonders they acknowledg'd him, I pretended</l>
                  <l>It was ſome ſpice, ſure of the falling ſickneſs,</l>
                  <l>And that was charity to bring him home;</l>
                  <l>They rub'd and chaf'd him, ply'd him with ſtrong water,</l>
                  <l>Still he was ſenſeleſs, clamors could not wake him;</l>
                  <l>I wiſhed 'em then get him to bed, they did ſo,</l>
                  <l>And almoſt fmothr'd him with rugges and pillows;</l>
                  <l>And 'cauſe they ſhould have no cauſe to ſuſpect me,</l>
                  <l>I watch'd them till he wak'd. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>'Twas excellent:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>When his time came to yawn, and ſtretch himſelf,</l>
                  <l>I bid 'em not to be haſty to diſcover</l>
                  <l>How he was brought home; his eyes fully open,</l>
                  <l>With trembling he began to call his ſervants,</l>
                  <l>And told 'em he had ſeen ſtrange viſions,</l>
                  <l>That ſhould convert him from his Heathen courſes;</l>
                  <l>They wondred, and were ſilent, there he preach'd</l>
                  <l>How ſweet the air of a contended conſcience</l>
                  <l>Smelt in his noſe now, ask'd 'em all forgiveneſs</l>
                  <l>For their hard paſture ſince they liv'd with him;</l>
                  <l>Bid 'em believe, and fetch out the cold ſur-loin:</l>
                  <l>Pierce the ſtrong beer, and let the neighbours joy in't:</l>
                  <l>The conceal'd Muskadine ſhould now lye open</l>
                  <l>To every mouth; that he would give toth' poor,</l>
                  <l>And mend their wages; that his doors ſhould be</l>
                  <l>Open to every miſerable ſutor.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>What ſaid his ſervants then?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy,</speaker>
                  <l>They durſt not ſpeak,</l>
                  <l>But bleſt themſelves, and the ſtrange means that had</l>
                  <l>Made him a Chriſtian in this over-joy,</l>
                  <l>I took my leave, and bad 'em ſay their prayers,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:32"/>
                  <l>And humor him, leſt he turned Jew agen.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Enough, enough. Whoſe this?</l>
                  <stage>Enter Toby.</stage>
                  <l>'Tis one of my ringers; ſtand cloſe, my Ladies Coachman.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>Buy a mat for a bed, buy a mat;</l>
                  <l>Would I were at rack and manger among my horſes;</l>
                  <l>We have devided the Sextons</l>
                  <l>Houſhould ſtuffe among us, one has the rugge, and he's</l>
                  <l>Turn'd Iriſh, and another has a blanket, and he muſt begge in't,</l>
                  <l>The ſheets ſerve another for a frock, and with the bed-cord,</l>
                  <l>He may paſs for a Porter, nothing but the mat would fall</l>
                  <l>To my ſhare, which with the help of a tune and a haſſocke</l>
                  <l>Out oth' the Church may diſguiſe me till I get home;</l>
                  <l>A pox a bell-ringing by the Ear, if any man take me</l>
                  <l>At it agen, let him pull mine to the Pillory, I could wiſh</l>
                  <l>I had loſt mine Ears, ſo I had my cloaths agen:</l>
                  <l>The wether wo'not allow this faſhion,</l>
                  <l>I do look for an ague beſides.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>How the raskal ſhakes?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>Here are company:</l>
                  <l>Buy a mat for a bed, buy a mat,</l>
                  <l>A haſſocke for your feet, or a Piſs clean and ſweet;</l>
                  <l>Buy a mat for a bed, buy a mat:</l>
                  <l>Ringing, I renounce thee, Ile never come to Church more.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>You with a mat?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>I am call'd.</l>
                  <l>If any one ſhould oſffer to buy my mat, what a caſe were I in?</l>
                  <l>Oh that I were in my Oat-tub with a horſe loaf,</l>
                  <l>Something to hearten me:</l>
                  <l>I dare not hear 'em;</l>
                  <l>Buy a mat for a bed, Buy a mat.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>He's deaf.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>I am glad, I am: buy a mat for a bed.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>How the raskal ſweats? What a pickle he is in?</l>
                  <l>Every ſtreet he goes through will be a new torment.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To.</speaker>
                  <l>If ever I meet at midnight more a jangling:</l>
                  <l>I am cold, and yet I drop; buy a mat for a bed, buy a mat.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>He has puniſhment enough.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Wildbrain.</stage>
                  <l>Who's this, my tother youth? he is turn'd Bear.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>I am half afraid of my ſelf: this poor ſhift</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:33"/>
                  <l>I got oth' Sexton to convey me hanſomely</l>
                  <l>To ſome harbour, the wench will hardly know me;</l>
                  <l>They'le take me for ſome Watchman oth' pariſh;</l>
                  <l>I ha ne're a penny left me, thats one comfort;</l>
                  <l>And ringing has begot a monſtrous ſtomacke,</l>
                  <l>And thats another miſchiefe, I were beſt go home,</l>
                  <l>For every thing will ſcorne me in this habit.</l>
                  <l>Beſides, I am ſo full of theſe young bell ringers;</l>
                  <l>If I get in adoors, not the power oth' countrey,</l>
                  <l>Nor all my Aunts curſes ſhall diſembogue me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Bid her come hither preſently,—hum; tis he. <stage>Exit. Ser.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>I am betraid to one that will eternally laugh at me,</l>
                  <l>Three of theſe rogues will Jeere a horſe to death.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lun.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis Mr. <hi>Wildbrain</hi> ſure, and yet me thinks</l>
                  <l>His faſhion's ſtrangely altred; ſirra Watchman,</l>
                  <l>You rugamuffin. turn you louzie bears skinne:</l>
                  <l>You with the bed-rid bill.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha'ſt found me out;</l>
                  <l>There's no avoiding him, I had rather now</l>
                  <l>Be arraign'd at Newgate for a robberie</l>
                  <l>Than anſwer to his Articles: your will ſir,</l>
                  <l>I am in haſte.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay then I will make bold wo' yee;</l>
                  <l>A Watchman and aſham'd to ſhew his countenance,</l>
                  <l>His face of authority; I have ſeen that phyſiognomy;</l>
                  <l>Were you never in priſon for pilfering?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>How the rogue worries me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur,</speaker>
                  <l>Why may not this</l>
                  <l>Be the villain rob'd my houſe laſt night,</l>
                  <l>And walks diſguis'd in this malignant rugge,</l>
                  <l>Arm'd with a tunne of Iron, I will have you </l>
                  <l>Before a Magiſtrate. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>What will become of me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>What art thou? ſpeak.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                  <l>I am the wandring Jew, and pleaſe your worſhip.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>By your leave Rabbi, I will ſhew you then</l>
                  <l>A Synagogue, iclip't Bridewell, where you </l>
                  <l>Vnder correction may reſt your ſelf;</l>
                  <l>You have brought a bill to guard you, there be dogwhips</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:33"/>
                  <l>To firke ſuch rugg'd curres, whips without bells </l>
                  <l>Indeed.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Bells.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>How he ſweats?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>I muſt be known, as good at firſt; now; jeere on,</l>
                  <l>But do not anger me too impudently, </l>
                  <l>The Rabbi will be mov'd then. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>How? <stage>lacke Wildbrain.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>What time oth' Moon man, ha? what ſtrange bells</l>
                  <l>Haſt in thy brains.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>No more bells,</l>
                  <l>No more bells, they ring backwards.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, where's the wench the bleſſing that befell thee?</l>
                  <l>The unexpected happineſs? where's that <hi>lacke?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhere are thy golden dayes?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>It was his tricke as ſure as I am louſie,</l>
                  <l>But how to be reveng'd—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Fie, fie, <hi>Iacke,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Marry a watchmans widdow in thy young dayes,</l>
                  <l>VVith a revennew of old Iron, and a rugge:</l>
                  <l>Is this the Paragon, the dainty Piece,</l>
                  <l>The delicate divine Rogue?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis enough I am undone,</l>
                  <l>Mark'd for a miſery, and ſo leave prating;</l>
                  <l>Give me my bill.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>You <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eed not aske your Taylors,</l>
                  <l>Vnleſs you had better linings; it may be</l>
                  <l>To avoid ſuſpition you are going thus</l>
                  <l>Diſguis'd to your fair Miſtreſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Mocke no further,</l>
                  <l>Or as I live Ile lay my bill o'thy pate,</l>
                  <l>Ile take a watchmans fury into my fingers,</l>
                  <l>To ha no judgement to diſtinguiſh perſons</l>
                  <l>And knocke thee down.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Come, I ha done, and now</l>
                  <l>VVill ſpeake ſome comfort to thee, I will lead thee</l>
                  <l>Now to my Miſtreſs hitherto conceal'd; </l>
                  <l>She ſhall take pity on thee too, ſhe loves</l>
                  <l>A ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſome man; thy miſery invites me</l>
                  <l>To do thee good, Ile not be jealous <hi>lacke;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Her beauty ſhall commend it ſelf; but do not</l>
                  <l>VVhen I have brought you into grace ſupplant me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Art thou in earneſt, by this could Iron—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>No oathes, I am not coſtive; here ſhe comes</l>
                  <stage>Enter Miſtreſs.</stage>
                  <l>Sweet heart, I have brought a gentleman,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:34"/>
                  <l>A friend of mint to be acquainted with you,</l>
                  <l>He's other than he ſeems; why d'ee ſtare thus?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh ſir, forgive me, I have done ye wrong.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>What's the matter? didſt ever ſee her aſore <hi>Jack?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Prethee do what thou wo't wo'me, if thou haſt</l>
                  <l>A mind, hang me up quickly.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Never deſpair, Ile give thee my ſhare rather,</l>
                  <l>Take her, I hope ſhe loves thee at firſt ſight,</l>
                  <l>She has Peticoates will patch thee up a ſuit;</l>
                  <l>I reſign all, onely Ile keep theſe trifles,</l>
                  <l>I took ſome pains for'em, I take it <hi>Jack;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>What thing you pinke of beauty, come let me</l>
                  <l>Counſel you both to marry, ſhe has a trade,</l>
                  <l>If you have audacity to hook in Gamſters:</l>
                  <l>Let's ha a wedding, you will be wondrous rich;</l>
                  <l>For ſhe is impudent, and thou art miſerable;</l>
                  <l>'T will be a rare match.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                  <l>As you are a man forgive me, Ile redeem all.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Yo wo'not to this geer of marriage then?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>No, no, I thank you <hi>Tom,</hi> I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n watch for</l>
                  <l>A groat a night, and be every gentlemans fellow. <stage>Exit Mi.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Riſe, and be good, keep home and tend your buſineſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou hak don't to purpoſe, give me thy hand <hi>Tom;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shall we be friends? thou ſeeſt what ſtate I am in,</l>
                  <l>Ile undertake this pennance to my Aunt,</l>
                  <l>Juſt as I am, and openly Ile go;</l>
                  <l>Where, if I be received again for currant,</l>
                  <l>And fortune ſmile once more—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, nay, I'me ſatisfied, ſo farewel honeſt louzie <hi>Jack.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>I cannot help it, ſome men meet with ſtrange deſtinies.</l>
                  <l>If things go right thou maiſt be hang'd, and I</l>
                  <l>May live to ſee't, and purchaſe thy apparel:</l>
                  <l>So farewel <hi>Tom,</hi> commend me to thy Polcat. <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <stage>Enter Lady, Nurſe, Servant.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Now that I have my counſel ready, and my cauſe ripe;</l>
                  <l>The Judges all inform'd of the abuſes;</l>
                  <l>Now that he ſhould be gone.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>No man knows whether,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:34"/>
                  <l>And yet they talk he went forth with a Conſtable</l>
                  <l>That told him of ſtrange buſineſs, that would bring him</l>
                  <l>Money and lands, and heaven knows what; but they </l>
                  <l>Have ſearch'd, and cannot find out ſuch an Officer:</l>
                  <l>And as a ſecret, Madam, they told your man</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nicholas,</hi> whom you ſent thither as a ſpie;</l>
                  <l>They had a ſhrewd ſuſpition 'twas the devil</l>
                  <l>Ith' likeneſs of a Conſtable, that has tempted him</l>
                  <l>By this time to ſtrange things; there have been men</l>
                  <l>As rich as he, have met convenient rivers,</l>
                  <l>And ſo forth; many trees have born ſtrange fruits:</l>
                  <l>De'e think he has not hang'd himſelf?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>If he be hang'd, who has his goods?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>They are forfeited, they ſay.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>He has hang'd himſelf for certain then,</l>
                  <l>Onely to coſen me of my Girles portion.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nu.</speaker>
                  <l>Very likely.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Or not did the Conſtable carry him to ſome priſon?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nu.</speaker>
                  <l>They thought on that too, and ſearch'd every where.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>He may be cloſe for treaſon, perhaps executed.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nu.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, they did look among the quarters too,</l>
                  <l>And muſtered all the bridge-houſe for his night-cap.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Servant.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, here is the gentleman agen.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>What gentleman?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>He that lov'd my young Miſtreſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas, 'tis <hi>Hartlove,</hi> 'twill but feed his melancholly,</l>
                  <l>To let him ſee <hi>Maria,</hi> ſince we dare not</l>
                  <l>Yet tell the world ſhe lives; and certainly,</l>
                  <l>Did not the violence of his paſſion blind him.</l>
                  <l>He would ſee paſt her borrowed tongue and habit.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nis.</speaker>
                  <l>Pleaſe you entertain him a while Madam,</l>
                  <l>Ile caſt about for ſomething with your daughter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Do what thou wor, pray Mr. <hi>Hartlove</hi> enter.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Hartlove.</stage>
                  <stage>Exit Ser. &amp; Nurſe ſeverally.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, I come to ask your gentle pardon.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Pardon, for what? you ne're offended me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, if ye be the mother of <hi>Maria.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>I was her mother, but that word is cancel'd,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:35"/>
                  <l>And buried with her in that very minute</l>
                  <l>Her ſoul fled from her, We loſt both our names</l>
                  <l>Of mother and of daughter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas, Madam,</l>
                  <l>If your relation did conſiſt but in</l>
                  <l>Thoſe naked terms, I had a title nearer,</l>
                  <l>Since love unites more than the tie of blood;</l>
                  <l>No matter for the empty voice of mother;</l>
                  <l>Your nature ſtill is left, which in her abſence</l>
                  <l>Muſt love <hi>Maria,</hi> and not ſee her aſhes</l>
                  <l>And memory polluted.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>You amaze me, by whom?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>By me, I am the vile profaner.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Why do you ſpeak thus indiſcreetly ſir?</l>
                  <l>You ever honour'd her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>I did alive,</l>
                  <l>But ſince ſhe died, I ha been a villain to her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>I do beſeech you ſay not ſo; all this</l>
                  <l>Is but to make me know, how much I ſinn'd</l>
                  <l>In forcing her to marry—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>Do not mocke me,</l>
                  <l>I charge you by the Virgin you have wept for;</l>
                  <l>For I have done an impious act againſt her,</l>
                  <l>A deed able to fright her from her ſleep,</l>
                  <l>And through her marble, oft to be reveng'd;</l>
                  <l>A wickedneſs, that if I ſhould be ſilent,</l>
                  <l>You as a witneſs muſt accuſe me for't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Was I a witneſs? </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, you knew I lov'd:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Maria</hi> once; or grant, you did but think ſo,</l>
                  <l>By what I ha profeſt, or ſhe has told you,</l>
                  <l>Was't not a fault unpardonable in me,</l>
                  <l>VVhen I ſhould drop my tears upon her grave,</l>
                  <l>Yes, and proof ſufficient. </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>To what?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>That I forgetfull of my fame and vowes.</l>
                  <l>To fair <hi>Maria,</hi> ere the Worm could pierce</l>
                  <l>Her tender ſhroud, had chang'd her for another;</l>
                  <l>Did you not bluſh to ſee me turne a Rebell?</l>
                  <l>So ſoon to court a ſhadow, a ſtrange thing,</l>
                  <l>VVithout a name? Did you not curſe my levity,</l>
                  <l>Or think upon her death with the leſs ſorrow</l>
                  <l>Thatſhe had ſcap'd a puniſhment more killing,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:35"/>
                  <l>Oh how I ſhame to think on't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir in my</l>
                  <l>Opinion, 'twas an argument of love</l>
                  <l>To your <hi>Maria,</hi> for whoſe ſake you could</l>
                  <l>Affect one that but carried her ſmall likeneſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>No more, you are too charitable, but</l>
                  <l>I know my guilt, and will from henceforth never</l>
                  <l>Change words with that ſtrange maid, whoſe innocent face:</l>
                  <l>Like your <hi>Maria's</hi> won ſo late upon me,</l>
                  <l>My paſſions are corrected, and I can </l>
                  <l>Look on her now, and woman kind, without</l>
                  <l>Love in a thought; 'tis thus, I came to tell you,</l>
                  <l>If after this acknowledgement, you'le be</l>
                  <l>So kind to ſhew me in what ſilent grave</l>
                  <l>You have diſpos'd your daughter, I will ask </l>
                  <l>Forgiveneſs of all her duſt, and never leave,</l>
                  <l>Till with a loud confeſſion of my ſhame</l>
                  <l>I wake her ghoſt, and that pronounce my pardon:</l>
                  <l>Will you deny this favour? then farewell,</l>
                  <l>Ile never ſee you more: ha!</l>
                  <stage>Enter Nurſe, Maria in her own apparel, after ſome ſhew of wonder he goes toward her.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Be not deluded ſir, upon my life</l>
                  <l>This is the ſoul whom you but thought <hi>Maria</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In my daughters habit; what did you mean Nurſe?</l>
                  <l>I knew ſhe would but cozen you, is ſhe not like now?</l>
                  <l>One dew unto another is not nearer.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nu.</speaker>
                  <l>She thinks ſhe is a gentlewoman;</l>
                  <l>And that imagination has ſo taken her,</l>
                  <l>She ſcorns to ſpeak, how handſomly ſhe carries it,</l>
                  <l>As if ſhe were a well bred thing, her body?</l>
                  <l>And I warrant you, what looks?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Pray be not fooliſh.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>I di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>turb no body, ſpeak but half a word</l>
                  <l>And I am ſatisfied, but what needs that?</l>
                  <l>Ile ſwear 'tis ſhe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>But do not, I beſeech you,</l>
                  <l>For truſt me ſir, you know not what I know.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>Peace then,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:36"/>
                  <l>And let me pray, ſhe holds up her hands with me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>This will betray all.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>Love ever honor'd,</l>
                  <l>And ever young, thou Soveraign of all hearts,</l>
                  <l>Of all our ſorrows, the ſweet eaſe,</l>
                  <stage>She weeps now.</stage>
                  <l>Does ſhe ſtill coſen me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nu.</speaker>
                  <l>You will ſee anon,</l>
                  <l>'Twas her deſire, expect the iſſue Madam.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>My ſoul's ſo bigge, I cannot pray; 'tis ſhe,</l>
                  <l>I will go nearer.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Algripe, Lurcher, Boy.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>Here's Mr. <hi>Algripe,</hi> and other ſtrangers Madam.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>Here good Lady,</l>
                  <l>Upon my knees I ask thy worſhips pardon;</l>
                  <l>Here's the whole ſumme I had with thy fair daughter;</l>
                  <l>Would ſhe were living, I might have her peace too,</l>
                  <l>And yield her up again to her old liberty:</l>
                  <l>I had a wife before, and could not marry;</l>
                  <l>My pennance ſhall be on that man that honor'd her,</l>
                  <l>To conferre ſome land.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>This is incredible.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis truth.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Do you know me ſir?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha, the gentleman I deceiv'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>My name is <hi>Lurcher.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>'Shat have thy morgage.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>I ha that already, no matter for the deed</l>
                  <l>If you releaſe it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile do't before thy witneſs;</l>
                  <l>But Where's thy ſiſter? if ſhe live I am happy, though</l>
                  <l>I conceal our contract, which was</l>
                  <l>Stoln from me with the evidence of this land.</l>
                  <stage>The Boy goes to Maria and gives her a paper; ſhe wonders, and ſmiles upon Hartlove, he amaz'd approaches her: afterward ſhe ſhews it her mother, and then givis it to Hartlove.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>Your daughter ſmiles.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>I hope ſhe lives, but where, I cannot tell ſir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Even here, and pleaſe you ſir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>How?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, 'tis ſhe;</l>
                  <l>To work thy fair way, I preſerved you brother,</l>
                  <l>That would have loſt me willingly, and ſerv'd ye</l>
                  <l>Thus like a boy; I ſerved you faithfully,</l>
                  <l>And caſt your plots to preſerve your credit;</l>
                  <l>Your foul ones I diverted to fair uſes;</l>
                  <l>So far as you would hearken to my counſel;</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:36"/>
                  <l>That all the world may know how much you owe me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>Welcome entirely, welcome my dear <hi>Alathe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And when I loſe thee agen, bleſſing forſake me:</l>
                  <l>Nay, let me kiſs thee in theſe cloaths.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>And I too,</l>
                  <l>And bleſs the time I had ſo wiſe a ſiſter, wer't thou the little thief?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſtole the contract, I muſt confeſs,</l>
                  <l>And kept it to my ſelf, it moſt concern'd me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>Contracted? this diſtroyes his after marriage.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <l>Dare you give this hand</l>
                  <l>To this young gentleman, my heart goes with it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Maria</hi> alive! how my heart's exalted, 'tis my duty;</l>
                  <l>Take her <hi>Frank Hartlove,</hi> take her; and all joyes</l>
                  <l>With her; beſides ſome lands to advance her Joynture:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>What I have is your own, and bleſſings crown ye.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>Give me room,</l>
                  <l>And freſh air to conſider, gentlemen,</l>
                  <l>My hopes are too high.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <l>Be more temperate,</l>
                  <l>Or Ile be Welſh again.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>A day of wonder.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Lady, your love, I ha kept my word; there was</l>
                  <l>A time, when my much ſuffering made me hate you,</l>
                  <l>And to that end I did my beſt to croſs you:</l>
                  <l>And fearing you were dead I ſtole your Coffin,</l>
                  <l>That you might never more uſurp my office:</l>
                  <l>Many more knacks I did, which at the Weddings</l>
                  <l>Shall be told of as harmleſs tales.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Wildbrain.</stage>
                  <stage>Shout within.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Hollow your throats a pieces, I am at home;</l>
                  <l>If you can roar me out again—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>What thing is this?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>A continent of fleas: room for the Pageant;</l>
                  <l>Make room afore there; your kinſman Madam.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>My kinſman? let me wonder!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Do, and Ile wonder too, to ſee this company</l>
                  <l>At peace one with another; 'tis not worth</l>
                  <l>Your admiration, I was never dead yet;</l>
                  <l>Ye'are merry Aunt, <hi>I</hi> ſee, and all your company:</l>
                  <l>If ye be not, Ile fool up, and provoke ye?</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46367:37"/>
                  <l>I will do any thing to get your love again:</l>
                  <l>Ile forſwear midnight, Taverns and temptations;</l>
                  <l>Give good example to your Grooms, the maids</l>
                  <l>Shall go to bed and take their reſt this year;</l>
                  <l>None ſhall appear with bliſters in their bellies.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>And when you will fool again, you may go ring.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, have mercy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Your ſubmiſſion ſir,</l>
                  <l>I gladly take, we will</l>
                  <l>Enquire the reaſon of this habit afterwards;</l>
                  <l>Now you are ſoundly ſham'd, well we reſtore you:</l>
                  <l>Where's <hi>Toby?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Where's the Coachman?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nur.</speaker>
                  <l>He's a bed, Madam.</l>
                  <l>And has an ague, he ſayes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile be his Phyſitian.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>We muſt a foot then.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lur.</speaker>
                  <l>E're the Prieſt ha done</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Toby</hi> ſhall wait upon you with his Coach,</l>
                  <l>And make your Flanders Mares dance back agen we'ye,</l>
                  <l>I warrant you Madam you are mortified,</l>
                  <l>Your ſute shall be granted too.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
                  <l>Make, make room afore there.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Home forward with glad hearts, home child.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                  <l>I wait you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                  <l>On joyfully, the cure of all our grief,</l>
                  <l>Is owing to this pretty little Thief.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt omn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>.</stage>
               </sp>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <head>The Actors Names.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>TOm Lurcher.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jack Wilbrain.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gentlemen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Justice Algripe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Frank Hartlove.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Toby.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Servants:</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sexton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bell-Ringers.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Boy.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Boy.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Lady,</hi> Mother to <hi>Maria.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Maria.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Nurſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Miſtreſs Newlove.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Women.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Miſtreſs.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:46367:37"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
